<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The honour of the taylors, or, The famous and renowned history of Sir John Hawkwood, Knight containing his many rare and singular adventures, witty exploits, heroick atchievements, and noble performances relating to love &amp; arms in many lands : in the series of which history are contained likewise the no less famous actions and enterprizes of others of the same art and mystery : with many remarkable passages relating to customs, manners &amp;c., ancient and modern : illustrated with pictures and embelished with verses and songs wonderfully pleasant and delightful : to which, as an appendix, is added a brief account of the original of the Worshipful Company of Merchant-Taylors, as to their being incorporated &amp;c., ...</title>
            <title>Honour of the Merchant Taylors</title>
            <author>Winstanley, William, 1628?-1698.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 209 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44299</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2599</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7888</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13518586</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13518586</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99890</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44299)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99890)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 790:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The honour of the taylors, or, The famous and renowned history of Sir John Hawkwood, Knight containing his many rare and singular adventures, witty exploits, heroick atchievements, and noble performances relating to love &amp; arms in many lands : in the series of which history are contained likewise the no less famous actions and enterprizes of others of the same art and mystery : with many remarkable passages relating to customs, manners &amp;c., ancient and modern : illustrated with pictures and embelished with verses and songs wonderfully pleasant and delightful : to which, as an appendix, is added a brief account of the original of the Worshipful Company of Merchant-Taylors, as to their being incorporated &amp;c., ...</title>
                  <title>Honour of the Merchant Taylors</title>
                  <author>Winstanley, William, 1628?-1698.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 55 p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Alexander Milbourn for William Whitwood ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption and running title: The renowned history of Sir John Hawkwood, Knight.</note>
                  <note>Written by William Winstanley.  Cf. DNB.</note>
                  <note>"This may be printed; R.P."</note>
                  <note>Advertisements: p. [3-4], [6]</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hawkwood, John, --  Sir, d. 1394.</term>
               <term>Merchant Taylors' Company (London, England) --  History.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99890:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99890:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Honour of the Taylors;</hi> OR, The Famous and Renowned HISTORY OF Sir <hi>Iohn Hawkwood,</hi> Knight. CONTAINING His many rare and ſingular Adventures, witty Exploits, heroick Atchievements, and noble Performances. RELATING TO LOVE &amp; ARMS, <hi>In many Lands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the SERIES of which Hiſtory are contained likewiſe, the no leſs Famous Actions and Enterprizes of Others of the ſame <hi>Art</hi> and <hi>Myſtery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With many Remarkable Paſſages, relating to Cuſtoms, Manners, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Ancient and Modern.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Illuſtrated with PICT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RES, and Embeliſhed with VERSES and SONGS, wonderfully pleaſant and delightful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To which (as an Appendix) is added,</hi> A Brief Account of the <hi>Original</hi> of the Worſhipful Company of <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant-Taylors,</hi> as to their being Incorporated, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Their Progreſs and Succeſs from time to time: The Favours they have received from divers Kings and Princes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Their many Structures of Magnificence and Charity; With many other things, exerting their true Worth and Grandeur.</p>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This may be Printed,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>R. P.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>Alexander Milbourn,</hi> for <hi>William Whitwood</hi> at the <hi>Golden Dragon</hi> next the <hi>Crown Tavern</hi> in <hi>West-Smithfield.</hi> 1687.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:99890:2"/>
            <head>The Hiſtory of Sir <hi>John Hawkwood,</hi> Knight.</head>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>Behold the <hi>Merchant-Taylor,</hi> and in's Hand</l>
               <l>A Meaſure, whilſt a Lady fair does ſtand</l>
               <l>Patient without a Bluſh, and lets him do</l>
               <l>What brave Gallants dare not pretend unto.</l>
               <l>When others pine but for a Glance, or Kiſs,</l>
               <l>By him the coyeſt Beauty handl'd is.</l>
               <l>Nor is his Trade inferiour to the beſt,</l>
               <l>For Art helps Natures Beauty when well dreſt,</l>
               <l>And Beauty is by Comlineſs expreſt.</l>
               <l>Firſt of all Trades this was, and did entice</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Adam</hi> to uſe it ev'n in <hi>Paradice.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:99890:2"/>
            <head>Books printed for <hi>W. Whitwood,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>The Illuſtrious Lovers, or Princely Adventures in the Courts of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France;</hi> containing ſundry Tranſactions relating to Love-Intrigues, noble Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes, and Gallantry; being an Hiſtorical Account of the Famous Loves of <hi>Mary,</hi> ſometimes Queen of <hi>France,</hi> (Daughter to <hi>Henry</hi> the 7th.) and <hi>Charles Brandon</hi> the Renowned Duke of <hi>Suffolk.</hi> Diſcovering the Glory and Grandeur of both Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Written Originally in <hi>French,</hi> and now done into <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lives and Actions of ſeveral notorious Counterfeits; who from the moſt Abject, and Meaneſt of the People, have Uſurped the Titles of Emperors, Kings and Princes; containing the Hiſtory of Twelve Infamous Impoſtors, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iz.</hi> 1. The falſe <hi>Smerdis,</hi> only Brother of <hi>Cambyſes,</hi> King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> and of the <hi>Medes.</hi> 2. The falſe <hi>Nero.</hi> 3. The falſe <hi>Meſſias,</hi> called <hi>Benchochab,</hi> Leader of the revolted <hi>Jews.</hi> 4. The counterfeit <hi>Moſes.</hi> 5. <hi>John Bulcold,</hi> King of the Anabaptiſts. 6. The falſe <hi>Clotaire,</hi> called <hi>Gondoald.</hi> 7. The counterfeit <hi>Baldwin,</hi> Earl of <hi>Flanders.</hi> 8. The counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit <hi>Don Sebaſtian,</hi> King of <hi>Portugal.</hi> 9. The counterfeit <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>oldomar,</hi> Elector and Marqueſs of <hi>Brandenburgh.</hi> 10. The falſe <hi>Muſtapha,</hi> Son of <hi>Baj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zet,</hi> the (firſt of that Name) Emperor of the <hi>Turks.</hi> 11. <hi>James Heraclides,</hi> the falſe Deſpot of <hi>Mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>davia,</hi> and <hi>Walachia.</hi> 12. <hi>Perkin Warbeck,</hi> or the counterfeit Duke of <hi>York.</hi> Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the Sr. <hi>J.</hi> B. <hi>de Rocoles,</hi> Hiſtoriographer of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Brandenberg.</hi> And now done into <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An exact Survey of the grand Affairs of <hi>France,</hi> in their particular conduct and management, ſince the concluſion of the Peace at <hi>Nimeguen.</hi> As they relate to that and other Kingdoms, but more eſpecially <hi>Spain, Savoy,</hi> and the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Wars, with the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Rebels;</hi> under the Leading of Count <hi>Teckeley,</hi> in Negotiations and other Affairs of State. Written lately in <hi>French,</hi> by a perſon of Quality made <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Hiſtory: or, a Relation of the Differences that happened in the Court of <hi>Spain,</hi> between <hi>Don John</hi> of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and Cardinal <hi>Ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ard;</hi> with other tranſactions of that Kingdom; together with all the Letters, politick Diſcourſes, Decrees, and other publick Acts that paſt between perſons of Quality, relating to thoſe Affairs.</p>
            <p>The Fortunate, the Deceiv'd, and the Unfortunate Lovers; three excellent new Novels, containing many pleaſant and delightful Hiſtories. Printed in <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>French,</hi> for the Ingenious. Written by the Wits of both Nations.</p>
            <p>Reflections on ſeveral of Mr. <hi>Dryden</hi>'s Plays; particularly on the Conqueſt of <hi>Granada,</hi> by <hi>E. Settle,</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>A Treatiſe of <hi>Lythotomy,</hi> or of the Extraction of the Stone out of the Bladder: wherein an account is given of the various Inſtruments uſed, and the Method obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in that curious, but difficult part of Chyrurgery, Illuſtrated with Twenty Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures curiouſly engraven on Copper Plates; written in <hi>French</hi> by Monſieur <hi>Tolit,</hi> Lythotomiſt of the Hoſpital of the Charity at <hi>Paris:</hi> tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh</hi> by <hi>A. Lovell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cochelearia Curioſa,</hi> or the Curioſity of Scurvy-Graſs, being an exact ſcrutiny and careful deſcription of the Nature and Medicinal Vertue of Scurvy-Graſs, in which is exhibited to publick uſe, the moſt &amp; beſt preparation for Medicines either for inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal or external uſe, in which that Plant, or any part thereof is imployed: together with an account of the ſeveral ſorts thereof, engraved on ſeveral Copper Plates: writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in Latin by Dr. <hi>Melimbrochius</hi> of <hi>Lipſwick,</hi> and Engliſhed by <hi>Tho. Sherley,</hi> M. D.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:99890:3"/>
            <p>The Hiſtory of the Siege of <hi>Rhodes,</hi> the firſt in the Reign of <hi>Mahomet</hi> the Great, Emperour of the <hi>Turks;</hi> the laſt under the command of <hi>Solyman</hi> the Magnificent, who at the Expence of 100000 Lives, totally ſubdued that Famous City and Iſland, deſended by the Valour of <hi>Peter d' Ambuſſon,</hi> Grand Maſter of <hi>Rhodes,</hi> and the Chriſtian Knights of the Order of St. <hi>John,</hi> againſt the whole power of the <hi>Ottomon</hi> Empire for 230 years.</p>
            <p>The Art of Short-Writing, according to <hi>Tachigraphy:</hi> Firſt Compoſed by Mr. <hi>Tho. Shelton,</hi> and Approved by both Univerſities. In which, Variety of Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to each Rule are drawn. Alſo Mr. <hi>Jer. Rich</hi> his Method of Contractions, by Ideas and Symbolical Characters; improved to the Rul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s and Methods of this, with great Eaſe, and no leſs Benefit and Delight. And dive<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s eminent Hiſtories out of the Old and New Teſtament, are repeated in words at length, and alſo in Characters. And laſtly, how to write the terms of the Law in Characters.</p>
            <p>The Hiſtory of the damnable Life and deſerved Death of Dr. <hi>John Fauſtus,</hi> the famous Conjurer of <hi>Germany;</hi> newly printed, according to the corrected Copy printed at <hi>Frankfort</hi> in <hi>Germany.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A true and perfect Account of the Examination, Confeſſion, Tryal, Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Execution of <hi>Joan Perry,</hi> and her two Sons, <hi>John</hi> and <hi>Richard Perry,</hi> for the ſuppoſed Murther of <hi>Will. Harriſon,</hi> Gent. being one of the moſt remarkable Occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences which ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h happened in the memory of man. Sent in a Letter, by Sir <hi>Tho. Overbury</hi> of <hi>Burton</hi> in the County of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> Knight, and One of His Majeſties Juſtices of the Peace, to <hi>Tho. Shirley,</hi> Dr. of Phyſick in <hi>London.</hi> Likewiſe Mr. <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon</hi>'s own Account, how he was conveyed into <hi>Turkey,</hi> and there made a Slave for above Two years; and then his Maſter which bought him there dying, how he made Eſcape; and what hardſhip he e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dured; who at laſt through the providence of God returned to <hi>England,</hi> while he was ſuppoſed to be murthered, here having been his man-ſervant Arraigned, who falſly impeached his own Mother and Brother, as Guilty of the mur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her of his Maſter: They were all Three Arraigned, Convicted, and Executed on <hi>Broadway Hill</hi> in <hi>Gloceſter-ſhire.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:99890:3"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>SEeing (moſt Ingenious Reader) that Hiſtories of this Nature have not only been approved as pleaſant, but profitable, in ſtirring up the Minds of <hi>Men</hi> (eſpecially of the younger ſort) to the Study of Ingenuity, and a Deſire of performing, and being capable of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking ſuch Enterprizes as upon ſundry Emergencies may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound to their Advantage; I could think of no better way or method, than to mingle <hi>Seriouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Mirth, Ingenious Stratagems</hi> and <hi>Policy,</hi> with <hi>War-like Exploits,</hi> and <hi>ſucceſsful Undertakings,</hi> in <hi>Love</hi> or <hi>Buſineſs;</hi> or what can be reaſonably imagined, that may the better ſuit with every Capacity. And of this kind, what can better employ them, than a H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtory of the Worthy Enterprizes of the <hi>Merchant-Taylors,</hi> who for their Ingenuity and Courage, have been no ſmall Honour to the Kingdom? But to expect I ſhould come to give a particular Account of the Bravery of each Individual, which Time h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Regiſtred in the golden Book of Fame, would be a Task too tedious (if not impoſſible) to be compiled in the Circle of an Age of Years. But ſince in what I have layd down, Much may be comprehended in a Little, and vie with, or out-do what has floridly been put (or impoſed, as we may ſay) upon other Trades, beyond their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, I ſhall in brief conclude in the <hi>Commendation</hi> of this Worthy Society, Corporation, or Trade, that for Loyalty, Ingenuity, Heroick Atchievements Charity, and many other matters, none have exceeded it, if (at leaſt) we ſhould ſubmit to an Equality. And ſo referring the Reſt to the Judgment of unbyaſſed Perſons, I remain an Honourer of the Members of this Firſt of Trades.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:99890:4"/>
            <head>Several Books Printed for <hi>William Whitwood</hi> at the <hi>Golden Dragon</hi> in <hi>Weſt Smithfield.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>CUrious Obſervations in that difficult part of Chirurgery, relating to the Teeth. Shewing how to preſerve the Teeth and Gums from all Accidents they are ſubject to. As, 1. An Account of their Nature. 2. Their Alteration, with their proper Remedies. 3. Their cauſe of corruption and putrefaction. 4. Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for reſtoring or ſupplying the defect of them in old or young. 5. Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions on the Tooth-Ach, looſeneſs of the Teeth, the decay of the Gums, with their Remedies and Reſtoratives. 6. The uſe of the <hi>Polican</hi> or Inſtrument wherewith they are drawn on all occaſions. Laſtly, Teeth in Children, what they are in the Original, and how they come to Perfection, in what order produced, the means to haſten them, and render them eaſie in breeding. To which is added, A Phyſical Diſcourſe, wherein the Reaſons of the beating of the Pulſe, or Pulſation of the Arteries, together with thoſe of the Circulation of the Blood are explained, and the Opinions of ſeveral Ancient and Modern Phyſicians and Phyloſophers; as <hi>Gallen, Gaſſendus, Carteſius, Lower, Willis,</hi> &amp;c. Upon this ſubject are examined.</p>
            <p>An Hiſtory of the twofold Invention of the Croſs, whereon our Saviour was Crucified, tranſlated out of an Antient <hi>Aramaean Biologiſt.</hi> Together with an account of the Converſion of the <hi>Ethiopians,</hi> out of <hi>Abulpharagius</hi>'s Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory; by <hi>Dudley Loftus, J. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>triuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </hi> Dr.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ovid</hi>'s Heroical Epiſtles, tranſlated into Engliſh, and illuſtrated with Twenty four Pictures, curiouſly engraved on Copper Plates.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>M. Juniani Juſtini. Ex Trogi Pompaei Hiſtoriis Externis Libri</hi> 44. 1. <hi>Notae Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectiſſime Voſſii, Bongarſii, &amp;c.</hi> 2. <hi>Variantes Lectiones in Margine Poſſita.</hi> 3. <hi>Chrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logicae Excerptiones Marginae quoque affixae, &amp;c. in uſum Sholaſtica Inventutis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reflections upon Ancient and Modern Philoſophy, Moral and Natural, together with the Uſe that there is to be made thereof; treating of the <hi>Egyptians, Arabians, Grecians, Romans, &amp;c. Philoſophers,</hi> as <hi>Thales, Zeno, Socrates, Pluto, Pythagoras, Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle, Epicurius,</hi> &amp;c. Alſo the <hi>Engliſh, German, French, Spaniſh,</hi> &amp;c. As <hi>Bacon, Boyle, Des Cartes, Hobbs, Van-Helmont, Gaſſendus, Gallilaeus, Harvey, Paracelſus, Mercennus, Digby.</hi> Tranſlated from the <hi>French</hi> by <hi>A. L.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Collection of Apothegms, or Sayings of the Ancients, collected out of <hi>Plutarch, Diogenes Laerthius, Elian, Atheneus, Stobaeus, Macrobius, Eraſmus,</hi> and others. Wherein the Manners and Cuſtoms of the <hi>Greeks, Romans,</hi> and <hi>Lacedaemonians,</hi> are repreſented. To which are added, ſeveral pleaſant Apothegms, from Modern Authors.</p>
            <p>A Rich Cabinet of Inventions, being Receipts and Conceits of ſeveral Natures, containing more than 130 Natural and Artificial Concluſions, all profitable and pleaſant. Collected out of <hi>Alexis, Mizaldus, Wecker,</hi> and the Practiſe of <hi>John White,</hi> Practitioner in the Mathematicks.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="history">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99890:4"/>
            <head>The Renowned Hiſtory OF Sir <hi>Iohn Hawkwood,</hi> Knight.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The Introduction; together with the Beginning of Renowned <hi>Hawkwood</hi>'s Love to fair <hi>Dorinda;</hi> And the Reſolution he took thereon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>WHen as <hi>England</hi> (after the Conqueſt) began to flouriſh in Trade and Manufacture, (enriched by the Induſtry of its Inhabitants, by traffiquing, as well abroad as at home, amongſt thoſe that contributed to its Promotion of this kind) the <hi>Merchant-Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors,</hi> then called <hi>Linnen-Armourers,</hi> were <hi>Eminent</hi> not only in Peace, but War; as amply appears by their <hi>many Noble Exploits,</hi> in Honour and Defence of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. And ſince they have been memorable on ſundry occaſions, I ſhall, to obliterate that wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch is objected againſt them, touching their Manhood, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> deliver (as I find them in their particulars and generals) a candid Relation as to matters of Love, Buſineſs, Witty Intreagues, and War-like Exploits, performed by ſundry Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies of this Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſion, which have raiſed them a Laſting Memory. And ſince <hi>Love</hi> is one principal Thread, whereby Hiſtories of this kind are faſtened to the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and good liking of the Reader, I think it altogether convenient to proceed regularly, and in order, that nothing may be omitted which is capable of adding a due Luſtre, or rendering the Vndertaking pleaſant and delightful; the Proof of which take as followeth:</p>
               <p>Amongſt other Youths whoſe diſcretions prompted them to undertake this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, was one <hi>John Hawkwood,</hi> of Parentage but mean, yet of a goodly Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, a quick App<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ehenſion, and ſound Iudgment, which afterward raiſed him to a conſiderable Degree and Advancement in the Record of never-dying Fame.</p>
               <p>This Youth having undertaken the Profeſſion of a <hi>Taylor,</hi> and by his neatneſs, activity, and dextetious performance, ſoon gained the Love and Applauſe of his Maſter, and his Cuſtomers, with many others, continuing to be reſpectful and obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to all manner of People: ſo that as he grew in Years, his Credit encreaſed, and with it his Ingenuity. But now (as it often happens to Young Men in the bloom of their days) he caſting his eyes upon <hi>Dorinda</hi> his Maſter's fair Daughter, a Virgin compleat in Beauty, and worthy to be beloved; it ſo happened, that by often feeding his fancy with the Fair Object, he became intangled in the ſnar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of Love, which for a while he ſtruggled with, or rather ſeemed to ſlight, as being altogether ignorant of its Power and Force; not conſidering, that like Lightning, the more it is oppoſed, the more Force it gathers, till breaking through the Cloudy Reſiſtance,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:99890:5"/> it makes the greateſt noiſe; that is, The more a Lover ſtrives to ſtifle his Flame, the hotter it burns, and torments him more than if he gave it vent. And this our Youth found in the end to be his caſe, and therefore began thus to debate with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: <hi>Well,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>and Muſt I give Love way? Muſt I yield to the Flames that he has kindled, or rather kindled by the Eyes of my Beloved Miſtris, who knows not (perhaps) what pain ſhe puts me to? or if ſhe did, the diſproportion being great, How can I with Reaſon expect a Cure? Tuſh, tuſh,</hi> continued the amorous Youth, <hi>Love is that which baffles Reaſon, and puts ſerious Conſiderations to flight: A thing that takes the Diadem from Queens, and makes a Conqueſt over Prince and Peaſant: Why then ſhou'd I diſpair? Although indeed I have but little ground to Hope, yet a tryal will be eaſie; and it is far better to run a hazard, than to live in pain: Fortune may ſo bring it about, that although the Fair One I admire be cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by many, ſhe may (notwithſtanding the ſeeming difficulty) be mine. <hi>Hellen</hi> at firſt was coy, yet <hi>Theſeus</hi> gained her love: And <hi>Paris,</hi> though a Shepherd, won her from a King. And why in this caſe may not the Lot be mine, amongſt ſo many Blanks, as if the chance ſeemed eaſier? It is but venturing; and come the worſt, I can but loſe what otherwiſe I never muſt expect.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Then caſting fear aſide, I will be bold,</l>
                  <l>And either fix more firm, or looſe my hold.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Having ſaid thus much, he reſolved to watch his opportunity, ſo that he might find a convenient time to tell his fair Miſtris how dear and tenderly he loved her, and how (without a ſuitable Return) he muſt remain unhappy. Nor was it long before he was poſſeſſed of ſo convenient a time; For looking out of his Chamber win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow in the Evening, he eſpyed the Ioy of his Heart going abroad by her ſelf; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, unknown to any of the Servants, or indeed to any of the Family, he followed her in the beſt Equipage the ſhortneſs of the time would permit him to furniſh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf withall; and although he was aſſured he had many Competitors, or Rivals, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to know his Doom,
<q>
                     <l>And to ſubmit to Fortune's ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ck<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e Will,</l>
                     <l>Whate'er ſhould be determin'd, good or ill.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>He makes known his Love to <hi>Dorinda,</hi> and is rejected; whereupon he returns home much diſſatisfied, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>OVr Youth reſolving upon what he had determined, and obſerving which way the fair <hi>Dorinda</hi> went, out-ſtripped her by a nearer path; and ſo opportunely meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he made his low, but amorous ſubmiſſion, paying his reſpects as on that occaſion was ſuitable; when as ſhe not ſuſpecting wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t was intended, but thinking he had met her by chance, began to queſtion him where he had been, as alſo of his buſineſs; to which he replyed, that <hi>His only buſineſs was to wait upon her, and to tender his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice with all the humble and endearing Reſpect imaginable; and that only in her Smiles he could be happy.</hi>
               </p>
               <figure/>
               <p>Vpon this, the Beauteous <hi>Dori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>da</hi> having pauſed a while, as one ſurprized at ſuch an unexpected Diſcourſe, or rather Demand of her Love, (which ſhe had not as yet fully determin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d to beſtow upon any) ſhe told him, <hi>That ſhe little expected to hear him ſpeak in ſuch a way, hoping (according to the moſt favourable conſtruction ſhe could make of it) that he was but in Jeſt: For if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e preſumed to inſiſt upon what he had mentioned, he might indeed deſpair of obtaining his Wiſh; and not only ſo, but incurr, in an high degree, both Hers and her Father's Diſpleaſure: But if he would be ſo prudent, as to ſpeak to her of Love no more, he might not only have a pardon for what was paſt, but expect to have it buried in Oblivion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Anſwer, returned with ſharpneſs and a contracted Brow, ſtruck our Lover with trembling and amazement, inſomuch, that for a time he knew not what to ſay: But after a while recollecting himſelf, he fell on his Knees before her, and intreated her, <hi>If he had offended, not to impute it to him, but to Love, whoſe irreſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtable Power, he hoped, would prove a ſufficient Plea to excuſe him; and tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> if Deſtiny had ſo ordered it, that he muſt ſtruggle with a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lame that in ſpight of reſ ſtance over-power'd him, he muſt ſubmit to his Fate.</hi> More he had ſaid, but whi ſt this Diſcourſe laſted, the fair <hi>Dorinda</hi> arrived at the houſe of a Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſin of hers, to which and, it ſeems, ſhe went abroad that Evening; and upon her having admittance, our Lover (penſive and melancholly) made his Retreat, blaming himſelf now for what
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:99890:6"/> he had undertaken, ſeeing he was ſo ſucceſſeſs in the Enterprize: And ſo returning home, he ſpent the following Night in much Anxiety, and in many reſtleſs Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations; ſometimes he concluded to be ſilent for the future; and at other times, thought that Captain a Coward who raiſed his Siege upon the firſt ſucceſſeſs aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault; but in the end, he reſolved by his Dutiful and Reſpective Behaviour towards her, to ingratiate himſelf into her good liking. And this, at this time, was his determination.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Hawkwood</hi> vexing himſelf, pined away: And how he diſcovered that <hi>Dorinda</hi> engaged her ſelf to <hi>Impolito,</hi> a young fooliſh Heir; and the Letters that paſſed upon that occaſion between her and <hi>Gaſpero</hi> his Uncle: With other matters and intreagues, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>OVr Youthful Lover having undertaken a Task of much difficulty, that is, bound himſelf from ſpeaking in the Dialect of Love, for fear of diſpleaſing his fair Miſtris, (for ſo ſhe had commanded) his Countenance, by the ardency of his Affections, was much altered, and he became lean and pining away, inſomuch, that it was taken notice of by moſt of the Houſe, and many asked and enquired into the Reaſon, yet could not get the Secret from him, but falſly conjecturing by his ſighing and hanging down his Head, that his Body was afflicted with ſome Diſtemper, when indeed the Diſeaſe was in his mind; and although ſhe, in whoſe power it was to cure it, neglected, and refuſed to apply the Balm of Condeſcending Kindneſs to the wound her fair Eyes had made, yet no Care was wanting in others to give him Eaſe: But alas! neither Druggs nor Potions can eaſe the Mind that labours under Love: Nor cou'd the Phyſician find the cauſe of his Diſtemper, but attributed it to the Effects of a Feaver; as indeed it was; but ſuch a one,
<q>
                     <l>As neither Skill, nor powerful Cordials fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ce,</l>
                     <l>Can from the Center of the Soul divorce:</l>
                     <l>For Love, as ſtrong as De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>th, derides all Art,</l>
                     <l>And Tyrant-like does triumph o're the Heart.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Our Lover, I ſay, being entangled in a ſnare, out of which (at that time) no means preſented a way for his Deliverance, but the yielding of his Dear <hi>Dorinda,</hi> or his pining into the Gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, he tormented himſelf long between Hope and Fear, as wretched Lovers do, who feed upon Camelion's Food, feed upon Imaginations, as thin as Air, and not ſo much available. Sometimes he repined at the Meanneſs of his Birth and Fortune; at other times he conceited a Secret Rival poſſeſſed that Heart which he ſo much deſired, and took up all the Room in fair <hi>Dorinda</hi>'s Breaſt: Oft he preſſed himſelf to enquire about it, but as oft was daſhed with the Fear of offending, ſince Silence was injoyned him. And ſo (toſſed like a reſtleſs Ship upon a ſtormy Sea) he continued many days, till at laſt, notwithſtanding all the ſeeming Coldneſs of his Miſtris, he diſcovered ſomething that gave him a light into the Cauſe of her refuſing him; for ſo it happened, That going abroad, as uſually ſhe did, under pretence of paying a Viſit to a Couſin of hers, ſhe forgot the Keys of her Cabinet, which our young Lover (whoſe Eyes were alwaies vigilant) perceiving, &amp; it coming into his Head, that by reaſon of her conference with an old Woman, who frequently came to enquire for her, that ſome Letters might happily be there, that might one way or other let him underſtand her Affairs, for he verily believed that Female Emiſſary might have more than Common Buſineſs with the fair <hi>Dorinda:</hi> This Curioſity prompted him to a ſearch, and there he found amongſt others theſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Letters.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:99890:6"/>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Mrs. <hi>Dorinda,</hi>
                        </salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I Underſtand by this faithful Bearer, in whom you may intirely confide, that you have (at my Requeſt) condeſcended to give my Nephew <hi>Impolito</hi> divers Meetings at your Couſin <hi>A. G</hi>'s. and have Promiſed him upon your <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Honour,</hi> that if he makes out the Eſtate he propoſes, you will conſent to be his Wife, laying aſide all other Scruples or Diſlikes; And if ſo, I doubt not but I ſhall ſoon ſee you happily joyned in Marriage: For if you can diſpenſe with his Awkwardneſs and Imbecility, as for the Reſt, you may aſſuredly take the Word of him who heartily wiſhes your ſpeedy Conjunction, and is</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Yours to ſerve you, <hi>A. Gaſpero.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Our Lover having read this, ſtood amazed, like one Thunder-ſtruck, and for a while knew not what to think or do; but in the end, recollecting his Manly Courage, and ſummoning all his Vigor to his aid, he proceeds to read the Second Letter written by fair <hi>Dorinda,</hi> in order (as is ſuppoſed) to ſend in Return to the former, with the firſt opportunity, it being then unſeal'd, and the Contents he found to be theſe.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>SIR,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I Muſt own, though with Bluſhes, that I have given your Nephew the opportunity to pay me ſome Viſits, beſides what has paſſed betwe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n us at a d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſtance, through the Care of your Truſty Friend, contrary to the Knowledge of my Parents, and have ſhunn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d the importunities of oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rs, the better to ſettle my Affections on him you have recommended to my Choi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e; for indeed, the large Overtures you have made on his behalf, and what himſelf has likewiſe d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>clared in that kind, may well make amends for the Defects that ſome more Curious Maidens might diſcover, in his want of Breeding and External Parts. But as for my ſhare, to deal ſincerely with you, I had rather have one I can live plentifully with, and do as I liſt, ſuch a one as will not controul me, nor pry into my ways, than a Sparkiſh Fellow, though never ſo comely and compleat, who will n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t only reſtrain me, but domineer, and render me perhaps not much Superior to a Slave. Wherefore no longer miſtruſting your Word, whom I have hitherto found a faithful Friend, you may let him know, that in my next I ſhall appoint a more private place of Meeting, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>re in ſhort the Nuptials may be cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated: And that the leſs notice may be taken, I will ſend him that notice by a truſty Friend of my own; And till then begging your favourable Conſtruction of this plain way of W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iting, contrary to the ſtile of Virgins on this oc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aſion, I reſt now not only your Friend, but</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Loving Kinſwoman in Conceit, <hi>Dorinda.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>If our Lover was before amazed, conſider here how much his wonder and aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment encreaſed: Nor for a long time could he ſpeak for ſighs and tears, though in the end theſe words found way: <hi>Alas!</hi> ſaid he, <hi>And is it poſſible, that</hi> Dorinda, <hi>fair and lovely</hi> Dorinda, <hi>who ſeems in all things ſo Reſerved, ſhould court a Man whom ſhe confeſſes to be ſo much defective; nay, rather that ſhe ſhould court (whoe'er he is, or whereſoe'er he is) his wretched Wealth, for that appears to be her Chiefeſt Aim? O Love!</hi> (continued he) <hi>Where is thy Power, thy Force, that thou ſuffereſt thy Laws to be thus violated, that</hi> Dorinda <hi>ſhould ſacrifice her ſelf to Covetous De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, and like a greedy Fiſh, reſolve to gorge the Bait that hides the Hook of ſo many Inconveniencies? And now too plain I ſee my Poverty's my Crime; my ill-Starr'd Fortune overbears my Happineſs, and ſtops my riſing Joys: Love, that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:99890:7"/> ſhou'd be free as Air, or Spirits unconfin'd, is bound in Golden Fetters; and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ence lock'd up in a Diamond Quarry. But what boots it that I now complain?</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>My Rival is unknown, nor does ſhe hear</l>
                  <l>Who all along has been to me ſevere:</l>
                  <l>Him ſhe has bleſt, whilſt me ſhe ſinks in Woe;</l>
                  <l>He laughs no doubt, whilſt I with grief o'reflow;</l>
                  <l>But come what will, it ſhall not long be ſo.</l>
                  <l>Something I'le do; and yet I know not what:</l>
                  <l>Reaſon aſſiſt me to contrive the Plot:</l>
                  <l>I'le try, if poſſible, to break this Knot.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Having ſaid thus much, he cloſed the Cabinet, leaving things as he found them: And ſo at that time compoſing himſelf as well as would conſiſt with the Diſorder he had to ſtruggle with, he paſſed about his occaſions penſive, and thoughtful who this <hi>Impolito</hi> ſhould be.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hawkwood</hi> finds out his Rival, and decoys him by means of a Letter, counterfeited in the name of <hi>Dorinda,</hi> to a Mad-houſe, and under pretence of his being diſtracted for Love, leaves him there.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>MVch grieved was our youthful Lover, to think his Miſtris ſhould ſo ſlightly give away her Heart, if thoſe may be ſaid ſo to do, who rather conſent to marry the Wealth than the Perſon, and are lured by Golden Promiſes into inſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Danger. And now he made it his buſineſs not only to have an Eye upon her, that he might the better underſtand whether ſhe perſiſted in her Reſolves, but alſo uſed ſuch Induſtry, that he found out his Rival, being (it ſeems) one whom Fortune, by the Induſtry of his Parents, had furniſhed with a plentiful Eſtate, but on the contrary, Nature had been unkind, in rumpling and diſtorting his Body in a diſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>derly form; and Wisdom had been as backward in furniſhing him with Vnderſtanding; yet (as the Old Proverb has it, conſidering <hi>Fools have Fortune</hi>) to this Medly of Creation, this Hotch-potch of a Man, the beautiful <hi>Dorinda</hi> gave the pledg &amp; plight of her Faith; ſo that nothing but the Nuptial Ceremony was wanting, and that, as you have heard, was fairly on the way: So that what to do in this caſe the Generous <hi>Hawkwood</hi> was at a loſs; Delay he knew would breed Danger and Diſcovery of the buſineſs to her Parents, who, for ought he knew, might allow her Choice was too Poor and Mean a Revenge, and might juſtly incurr her everlaſting Hatred: So that being in a manner diſtracted in his opinions, he ſometimes began to think of Revenge and a Reſolution to loſe his Life or ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>'s Blood; but that again was daſhed and checked by other Reſolutions; ſo that in the end he came to a Point, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded on a notable Str<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tagem, which he put in execution after this manner:</p>
               <p>Vnderſtanding fair <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> had ſent the Letter, wherein ſhe promiſed to appoint <hi>Impolito</hi> a private Meeti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g &amp;c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>herea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Novice was not a little over-joyed, largel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> provid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gainſt the happy expected day. Young <hi>Hawkwood</hi> takes his opportunity to put him<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>f in the beſt E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>page he could, and gravely goes to a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>octo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> little <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> from the Town, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe buſineſs it was to undertake the Cure of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch as w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e diſtracted, and tells him a very formal Story, That a y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g Ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an of his, the Hope and F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er of his Family, Rich and Young, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nhappily <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ove w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h a ſcornful you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g Gentlewoman, by whom he (after
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:99890:7"/> ſome hopes of gaining her favour) had been ſlighted and rejected, the which, together with other Diſorders and Infirmities of Mind, upon the ſudden news of her Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, had wonderfully diſcompoſed and crazed his Wits, inſomuch, that daily grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing worſe and worſe, he feared in the end it might turn to an incurable Phrenzy, if not timely redreſſed, and the thoughts of his paſt-misfortune put out of his mind; for that in his Ravings he talked of nothing but Women, Aſſignations, Appointments, and Love-Intreagues, frequently enquiring for, and calling upon one <hi>Dorinda,</hi> who indeed was the Chief cauſe of his diſorder.</p>
               <p>The Doctor having heard this plauſible Story, began to pitty the Youth, commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerate his misfortune, and exclaim againſt her that had occaſioned it; withal, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to do his utmoſt, in order to the Reſtoring of him to his Right Senſes, bidding him neither deſpair of, nor fear his Recovery: Nor would he uſe him roughly, but as tenderly as the thing required. This diſcourſe of the Doctor's tickled the Fancy of Young <hi>Hawkwo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d,</hi> who had in his Imagination already accompliſhed his deſign; ſo that appointing to bring him within three days with the Overture of a Good Reward, he took his leave: So that now he had no more to do, than to frame a Letter in the Name of <hi>Dorinda,</hi> to bring the Woodcock into the ſnare.</p>
               <p>Being come home, and finding ſome Papers that <hi>Dorinda</hi> had written on ſundry trivial occaſions, to ſlip no time, leſt he ſhould be anticeeded, he ſits him down, and ſo exactly counterfeited, in her Hand, the following Letter, that without great diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty it could not be diſtinguiſhed even by her ſelf: For in this Craft great was his Ingenuity, as well as in many others, that gained him Applauſe and Admiration a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Youths, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Contents of the Letter were theſe:
<floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>My Dear <hi>Impolito,</hi>
                           </salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>REmember, (if your Uncle has communicated ſo much to you) that in my laſt (waving further Complements) I informed you, that I would appoint a certain place of private Meeting, where, without any interruption or diſturbance, by the Confluence and Corcourſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>riends, we might finiſh the Ceremonies of our Love: Wherefore, (to prevent the Interpoſal of any Envious Perſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>n, whoſe Malice to you or my ſelf, under pretence of Love and Affection, or for many Ends to us unknown, may forbid the Banes; for I am not ignorant, that you have ſome Friends, and I ſome Pretenders, that would will<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ngly Croſs our Loves, if they could diſcover them) wherefore, I ſay, to prevent the worſt, as ſoon as this Letter ſhall come to your Hands, make what proviſion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> you think convenient, and without acquainting any Perſon with the Contents, put your ſelf upon the Conduct of this faithful Bearer, who will bring you to the Place, where (with ſome few of our Friends and Confidents) I am ready to receive and welcome you; And when the danger of preventing our Nuptial is paſt, when the Sacred Knot is tyed too faſt for Envy to break, then will we ſend for the reſt of our Friends and Acquaintance, and Tune our Happineſſes to louder Joy. And ſo my Dear <hi>Impolito,</hi> in ſpeedy expectation of your much-deſired Company, I reſt,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Your conſtant and faithful <hi>Dorinda.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>The Letter being thus aptly framed to the purpoſe, leſt delays might prevent the Deſign, he poſts away early the next morning, and as Luck would have it, meets <hi>Impolito</hi> juſt coming out of his Vncles Gate; him he ſalutes, and with many Crin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges delivers him the Letter, telling him withal from whom he brought it; which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he might have ſpared; for he verily concluded upon the firſt ſight of the Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, that it could be no other than <hi>Dorinda</hi>'s Hand, and thence gueſſing at the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:99890:8"/> Contents, had ſcarce (for the Tranſport of Ioy he ſeem d to be in) Patience to open it, asking in the mean time Twenty Queſtions, one upon the neck of another; to which, as far as convenient, the witty <hi>Hawkwood</hi> returned ſuitable Anſwers: But when he had opened it, and perceived by Part what the Whole meant, impatient of delay or loſs of time, he embraced the Meſſenger as in a paſſionate manner, and cryed out, as in an Extaſie, <hi>O dear friend! how much am I beholden to thee, for bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me this Happy News! and how much may you hereafter expect of me for your Labour!</hi> And thereupon catching him by the hand, without any Enquiry who he was, or where he lived, he pulled him on, ſaying, <hi>Come my lucky Pilot, ſhew me the way, without longer tarrying, to my Haven of Happineſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hawkwood</hi> perceiving Fortune favour him in this Enterprize, lead him (the leſs to be obſerved) all the by-ways imaginable, and held him in pleaſant Diſcourſe, till they came within ſight of the Doctor's Houſe, at which time having heard the Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent Diſcourſe of his Rival, he began to have ſome relenting in his mind, and to pitty his Imbecility; but the Hard-heartedneſs of the fair <hi>Dorinda</hi> towards him, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>opes he had by that Artifice to break off the Match, (after ſome Reluctancy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer'd all Compaſſion, and) put him upon a tryal of the credulous Youngſter's Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: So that making up to the Houſe, he boldly knocked at the door, and ſoon found admittance, by the means of him that waited; when whiſpering him in the Ear after he underſtood the Doctor was within, he bid him tell him, that he had brought his Couſin, and was deſirous to attend him in his retirement. With this requeſt the Servant readily acquaints his Maſter, who gave order, That <hi>Hawkwood</hi> (to whom he gave the ſtile of <hi>Gentleman</hi>) ſhould be admitted, commanding him that waited; to entertain the Young-man the mean while with ſome Pleaſant Stories of Love, the better to keep him in Countenance, whilſt matters might be ordered to diſpoſe of him. All this being exactly obſerved, our Witty Youth being arrived at the Study of this grave Profeſſor, after having made his Complement, began to make a Repetition of what he had told him before: and withal, that no Coſt ſhould be ſpared, if, by his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, he reſtored his Kinſman to his Vnderſtanding and diſpoſſeſſed him of the diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of his Mind, which he that Pretended to all things made no Bones to Promiſe; and thereupon he gratified him with a Sum that proved (at preſent) ſatisfactory, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring to be let out a back-way, leſt otherwiſe the parting might be tedious and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome wonderfully ſuggeſting the affections of <hi>Impolito</hi> towards him, or rather that upon his leaving him, he might fall into a raving Fit, to his further prejudice. This, upon the propoſal of a Day of Return, was granted; and ſo the witty <hi>Hawkwood</hi> is diſmiſſed, leaving the unthinking Cully in the Trap, though at preſent overwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with Ioys, in expectation of finding his <hi>Dorinda</hi> there.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>So to the Snare the Bird (unthinking) flyes,</l>
                  <l>Not doubting there his Hunger to ſuffice,</l>
                  <l>But ſoon convinc'd is by a ſad ſurprize.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Impolito</hi> the Rival of <hi>Haw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d</hi> was handled in the Mad-houſe; As alſo his diſcourſe with the Doctor: The Miſery he underwent; And the means by which he was diſco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ered and ſet free: With other matters and things, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>NO ſooner had our Ingenious Youth performed what he intended, and made his eſcape, but down came the Man in the Whiskers to poor <hi>Impolito,</hi> who, till he was deceived, imagined at the ſound of every ſtep it was his Miſtris the fair <hi>Dorinda,</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:99890:8"/> which had cauſed him to draw nearer and nearer the Foot of the Stairs, thinking no leſs than that <hi>Hawkwood</hi> went up to inform her of his arrival; but upon the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of him I have mentioned, he imagined it might be her Father, whom he indeed had heard of, but never ſeen, and ſo (not altogether forgetting his Duty) he fell on his Knees, and anticipated what he was about to ſay to him, by asking him Bleſſing. This poſture ſo unexpectedly, and out of ſeaſon, to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ether with the mention of <hi>Dorinda</hi> to marry, (of whom, it ſeems, he asked Conſent, with many proteſtations of his Love and Sincerity) confirmed the old Gentleman in all that <hi>Hawkwood</hi> had told him; and thereupon taking him from the ground, he began to fumble his Pulſes, and conſider the working of his Temple-Veins, which through the vehement agitation of his paſſionate expreſſions, were not in a little diſorder: The Youngſter the mean while wondering what was meant by this unuſual handling; yet continuing his diſcourſe of Love, with many Cringes, he began at laſt to enquire for his Miſtris, declaring how he was ſent for, and to what intent he came. <hi>Well, well,</hi> ſaid the old Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>be not too haſty Swe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>art, and I will go up and ſend her down to you.</hi> But no ſooner had he left him in expectation of ſuch an Happineſs, but at the ringing of a Bell, two or three luſty fellows entred at another door, and catching poor <hi>Impolito,</hi> carried him forcibly up Stairs, where clapping him into a warm Bed, provided for the purpoſe, they bound him down with Cords, and ſo (whilſt he remained in much Conſternation and Confuſion, wondring what was intended) they poſed him as bare as a Coot, by ſhaving off his Hair; after which, the old Gentleman accoſted him with his Inſtrument, and other Furniture, uſeful on that occaſion, bleeding him on both Arms till ſuch time as he became exceeding faint, and ſeconded that with ſundry Applications and Medicaments; no Intreaty of his, nor Relation of what he was, or to whom he appertained, was any ways availing to prevent it; for the more he told the ſtory of his Love, and the End of his coming thither, the more he increaſed (in the opinion of thoſe that had to do with him) the Conception of his Diſtemper; all his ſerious Proteſtations, and earneſt Aſſeverations of what he was, and to whom he was allyed, being only taken for Ravings, and the Defects of a diſorderly mind; ſo that in the end, through Phyſick, unuſual Dyet, and Impatiency, he was in a manner what (by miſtake) they had taken him for.</p>
               <p>Young <hi>Impolito</hi> remaining in this plight, great was the Enquiry after him, and the rather, becauſe <hi>Dorinda</hi> had ſome hours after his departure ſent a Letter, much to the ſame effect as the former; ſo that after three days abſence, and no intelligence of him, they began to imagine ſtrange things: The Vncle, that he was Spirited away; and <hi>Dorinda,</hi> that he ſlighted her, either abſconding or denying himſelf; and others had their peculiar and different Conceptions of the matter. But ſo it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, That after a tedious ſearch, and the exact Deſcription of him to divers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in thoſe Parts, with promiſes of Rewards and Gratuities, Information was brought to <hi>Gaſpero</hi> in whoſe hands he was, who coming thither, found him in a ſtrange condition, brought, by his Vſage and Dyet, ſo low, and ſo much altered, that it was difficult to know him. <hi>Impolito,</hi> upon the ſight of his Vncle, cryed out, and made a grievous Complaint, declaring how he was trappan'd, and what miſeries he had undergone, withal, producing the Letter he had received, which being compared with what <hi>Dorinda</hi> had afterward ſent, agreeing much in the Subſtance, and more in the Hand, it was concluded to be an Artifice of hers; for that the Intreague of their loves being all along kept ſecret, it could not be thought that ſuch a buſineſs could be contrived without her knowledge; and that on which this ſuſpicion was the rather grounded, was her ſudden condeſcenſion. And with this, and what elſe had
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99890:9"/> happened, the old Woman who was Houſe-keeper to <hi>Gaſpero,</hi> was ſent to acquaint her, who was indeed as yet ignorant of the particulars of what had happened; nor was ſhe a little amazed when ſhe heard them, proteſting her ignorance and innocency. As for the Doctor, he begged Pardon for what he had done, pretending and alledging it was done through miſtake, though by him deſigned to a good intent; that he had been impoſed upon, and was ſorry and aſhamed he had been ſo deceived and abuſed: But ſo lively deſcribed the Party that committed <hi>Impolito</hi> to his cuſtody, that he was (not long after) diſcovered: As will appear in the following Chapter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The Plot ſucceeding to <hi>Hawkwood</hi>'s wiſh, the Match is broken off: <hi>Impolito</hi> is ſent into the Country; And <hi>Gaspero</hi> his Uncle ſeeks and concludes to revenge the Affront: With the manner of his Reſolution.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THe Lovers thus croſſed in their expectation, the croſs accident (through many thwartings that ariſe) created ſo great a miſunderſtanding between them, that by degrees they became cold to what before they ſo hotly were intent upon; &amp; the rather, for that <hi>Impolito</hi> being much weakened, and out of order, was ſent into the Country to recover his Health, and ſoon after, for the bettering his Vnderſtanding, into For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Parts, under the Protection of a Tutor: Where, for a while, we will leave him.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Thus <hi>Hawkwood</hi>'s Plot ſucceeds in the firſt part:</l>
                  <l>But yet he gains not fair <hi>Dorinda</hi>'s Heart.</l>
                  <l>Though ſomewhat pleas'd that he ſucceeds ſo well,</l>
                  <l>That yet ſome Hopes within his Breaſt may dwell.</l>
                  <l>Hope, that doth feed the labo'ring Thought of Man,</l>
                  <l>And is a <hi>Medium</hi> 'twixt their Joy and Pain,</l>
                  <l>Carrying ſome Pleaſure where Men hope in vain.</l>
               </q>
               <p>By this means, I ſay, <hi>Hawkwood</hi> being freed from what he before apprehended would ſuddenly leave him no place for Hope, rejoyces like a reprieved Malefactor, that (at leaſt) he has gained Time, though not the utmoſt of his Wiſh, and by new Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices ſtrives what he can to appear ſomething in the Eyes of fair <hi>Dorinda,</hi> who had by this time caſt off the diſturbance ſhe was in, and concern for what had ſo lately happened, which required not much difficulty, ſeeing in that Match ſhe rather ſtrove to gratifie her Ambition than Love; but ſtill he found her the ſame towards him: Sometimes indeed ſhe would ſeem to give him a Smile, but then again would deſtroy that favour with a Frown; during which time, the reſtleſs <hi>Gaſpero</hi> had uſed his utmoſt diligence to find out the Author of the Intreague before mentioned, breathing nothing but Threats of Revenge; and was ſo ſucceſsful, by the Deſcription, and other Circumſtances, that he pitched upon <hi>Hawkwood</hi> to be the man; and the rather, for that (at that very time) he was not only abſent from his Maſter's Houſe, but was ſeen returning from that of the Doctor's: and therefore verily concluding, that it had been contrived by him and <hi>Dorinda,</hi> not ſo much for his Nephew's diſgrace, as his own, who had ſo earneſtly laboured in the buſineſs: He concluded ſometimes on one thing, and ſometimes on another, to revenge the Affront: Sometimes he thought to make known what had happened to <hi>Dorinda's</hi> Father, and to demand a publick acknowledgment and ſatisfaction: At other times he thought this low, and vow'd
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:99890:9"/> to Right the Injury by Law; but theſe were daſhed, upon the conſideration of the Propoſals he had made to <hi>Dorinda, viz.</hi> That in caſe the Marriage ſucceeded, all the Rents and Profits he had already received of his Nephew's Eſtate, ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound to himſelf: and this covetous Reaſon was the only one, for which he was ſo earneſt, in contriving and clapping up a private Match. So that waving theſe, he reſolves on a private Revenge, whereby (as he ſuppoſed) the Suffering of the one might redound either to the Grief or Shame of the other; for he verily believed, that upon <hi>Dorinda's</hi> little Concern for the breaking off the Match, that another had gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her Heart; and ſo proceeded to conjecture this might be him: Whereupon, blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by Paſſion and Miſtake, he at firſt reſolved upon a fatal way to make a Separation, which was by procuring him privately to be murthered: But again, upon ſecond thought, weighing the dangerous conſequences, if it ſhould be diſcover'd, he conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himſelf to change it into an extraordinary Beating or Cutting, which might prove more laſting and painful than the former: and this was his abſolute determination.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Gaſpero</hi> being ſtill reſolved upon Revenge, accidently happens on <hi>Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iel</hi> and <hi>Bragwell,</hi> two Ruffians, to whom he commits the Puniſhment of <hi>Hawkwood;</hi> and by what means it is to be brought about.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>GAſpero</hi> having decreed as aforeſaid, yet not daring to attempt it himſelf, it ſo hapned: As he was looking out of his Window one Evening, he eſpyed two Ruffian-like fellows walking careleſly in the ſtreet, appearing by their Garb and Motion to be deſtitute both of Money and Imployment; inſomuch, that at that time it came into his Head, that theſe were wonderful ſitting to execute his Revenge: Wherefore, when he had a little narrowlier obſerved them, he ſent a little Youth he kepe to run on Errands after them, with order to invite them to his Houſe. Theſe Fellows, who would have run a Mile to a Three-penny Ordinary, upon this Invita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, began to wonder what it ſhould mean, yet ſtood not to diſpute the matter, but followed the Youth, as ſuppoſing to what end ſoever it was, it could not be to their prejudice: And ſo being brought into the Hall, the Boy went up to his Maſter, and informed him, that the Men he had ſent for were below, and waited his good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; whereupon he ordered him to carry them into his Parlour, and ſet before them ſuch Meat and Drink as the Houſe at that time afforded; which was done with all convenient ſpeed. This unexpected Entertainment did not a little ſurprize them, for Now or Never they thought they had met with their good Angel, which made them ſmile upon each other, and ask the Boy the cauſe, who told them, he knew no other than that it was his Maſter's good pleaſure. Then began they to conclude, that this was ſome Gentleman, of an Ancient Family, who generouſly (though contrary to the faſhion) kept up the Hoſpitality of his Anceſtors; and ſo, without any further ſcruple, fell on feeding and carrouſing, not only for preſent ſatisfaction, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut to pay their hungry Bellies the Arrears of divers days before, wherein they had Dined at Duke <hi>Humphry</hi>'s.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Gaſpero</hi> ſuppoſed his new-come Gueſt had well refreſhed themſelv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, he came into the Room, and whilſt they ſtood cringing and complementing, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id them heartily welcome; and ſo commanding the Boy away, after a Glaſs or two had gone round, he ſaid, <hi>Gentlemen, you may well wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>der that (you being Strangers to me) I have taken upon me to invite you into my houſe; for indeed (as I rem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mber) I have n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:99890:10"/> ſeen either of you before I ſaw you paſſing by: But</hi> (continued he) <hi>Gentlemen, there is more in it (perhaps) than you can gueſs at, or I am willing, without a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Promiſe of Secreſie, to divulge unto you: Promiſe me, I ſay, to keep Secret what I ſhall propoſe to you, and if when it is propoſed, you will undertake it, you ſhall be bountifully rewarded: Or if you refuſe it, in conſideration that it may ſpread no further, and that thereon you will plight and engage your faiths and troths, you ſhall not go altogether empty-handed from my Houſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This kind of Diſcourſe made the two Ruffians ſtare upon each other, as not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for ſome time what to reply; but being men of a deſperate Fortune, at length waxing bold one of them brake the ſilence, and ſaid, <hi>Sir, your Bounty towards us has already ingag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d us to oblige you in any thing that is within our power; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for my p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rt, I ſhall be willing to be directed by you in any thing that may ſtand with your conveniency or good-liking; and as for your miſtruſting our fidelity, let that be far from you.</hi> Thus ſaid the one, and the other confirmed it as the Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of his Mind; and in brief, both of them made ſuch Proteſtations, that <hi>Gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pero</hi> ſtood no longer doubtful, but opened all the buſineſs to them, from the beginning to the ending, aggravating the Affront, and requiring them to revenge it, in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting what he had determined on <hi>Hawkwood.</hi> This without further delay they promiſed to undertake, and ſeemed to rejoyce, that an opportunity of that kind was put into their hands to ſerve him; and then murmured, that him they were to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take was not ſome Gyant, or Monſter of a Man, that in exerting their Valour, their Zeal to ſerve him might more eminently appear; or that it was not their happineſs to engage with odds of number; boaſting at a large rate their wonderful Exploits and valiant Atchievements; adding, that in this caſe the Affront being ſo great, in their opinions, Murther was too ſmall a Revenge, if it was poſſible it could be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried further.</p>
               <p>Theſe Expreſſions delivered with ſo much Bravado, made <hi>Gaſpero</hi> conceive he had happened on the moſt worthy Champions of the World, and began to compute <hi>Guy, Bevis,</hi> and the Ancients, but Child<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en to theſe; and thereupon perceiving they wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted convenient Weapons to mawl the Youngſter, who all this while was ignorant of what was intended againſt him, impatient of delay, he runs to his Armoury, and fetches a couple of ruſty Back-ſwords, made in the days of his great Grandfather, and theſe he recommends as fit Inſtruments of his Indignation; but withal, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands them they ſhould proceed no further than to cutting and ſlaſhing, or make him compound for his Life with the loſs of a Limb, or the like. But now a greater diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty was ſtarted, <hi>viz.</hi> how they ſhould conveniently light on young <hi>Hawkwood,</hi> ſo that when they had accompliſhed their buſineſs, they might eſcape undiſcovered: one while they were for watching his going abroad; at another, to find ſome quaint De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to get him abroad by a wile, as he had done <hi>Impolito,</hi> or to ſend for him in a feigned Name: Many things they ſuggeſted of this kind, and often randyed about the matter; when in the end, the old blade bethought himſelf that <hi>Green-Gooſe Fair,</hi> annually kept at <hi>Bow</hi> by <hi>Stratford,</hi> was on the following <hi>Monday,</hi> which lucki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly happened to be St. <hi>Willielmus</hi> day, who is much honoured by the Taylors, as their Patron, and in honour of whom, they for the moſt part keep every <hi>Monday</hi> Holy-day, as thoſe of the Gentle-Craft do for St. <hi>Criſpin.</hi> To this place he doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not but young <hi>Hawkwood</hi> (who was ever frolick and gay) would reſort; and that upon his return ſingling him from his Company, they might (under ſome pretence of ſcraping acquaintance) uſe him at their pleaſure: and the better to know him, that they might not be miſtaken in the man, one of them was to go to his Maſter's Houſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:99890:10"/> in the habit of a Porter, to deliver a Letter, as brought up by the Carrier, from a Friend of his in the Country: All which ſucceeded ſo to their wiſh, that having a good Stipend in hand, and larger promiſes when the buſineſs was effected, they laid their Ambuſh, though to their ſmall advantage; as in the following Chapter will appear.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Hawkwood</hi> (coming from <hi>Green-gooſe Fair</hi>) was ſet upon by Two Ruffians, hired by <hi>Gaspero;</hi> and how he left them for dead: The conſternation he was in, and the debate with himſelf about his departure: The Lines he left for <hi>Dorinda:</hi> His ſetting forward unknown to the Family; and the conſternation it occaſion'd.</p>
               </argument>
               <figure/>
               <p>AS Fortune or Fate would have it, young <hi>Hawkwood</hi> anſwered their expectation ſo pat, in making it his Recreation to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lk to the Fair, that they could not wiſh (as they thought) any thing to fall out better: When having dogged him a great part of the day, when the evening approached, they perceived by his taking leave of his Company, who were revelling with their Laſſes, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e was about to return home; and ſo it happened to further what they poſſibly could expect: That notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Iollities of the day, he being ſomewhat melancholly for the ſcorn where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with <hi>Dorinda</hi> ſeemed to treat him; and for that, ſince the departure of <hi>Impolito,</hi> ſhe ſeemed to caſt her favours on another ſuch-like of a Medly of Creation, of whom I ſhall ſay ſomething hereafter; he, to avoid the concourſe on the main Road, and ſhun the company of thoſe of his Profeſſion, who (in the height of their merriment<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he well knew, would entice him to ſtay abroad late, which was not his cuſtom; he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I ſay, to do this, took his way the fartheſt about, through the lonely fields, very few Buildings being (in thoſe days) between that and <hi>London:</hi> And now <hi>Dareill</hi> and <hi>Bragwell</hi> (for ſo they were called) thinking themſelves cock-ſure of doing what they had undertaken, paſſed him, who in his penſive mood took little notice of them, as being ignorant of their purpoſe: But coming to a convenient place; (it being now dusk
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:99890:11"/> in the Evening) they loytered for him, ſuffering him to overtake them, and then, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter giving him ſome opprobrious words, from which he gathered what they intended, and ſhrewdly gueſſed at the cauſe, and would have made ſome Reply, but they ſo furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly fell upon him, who had no weapon to defend himſelf, that they prevented it; for now he that in One Man had never met with his equal in ſtrength thought that Now or Never was the time of trying his utmoſt force; and therefore, without any words, having received ſeveral ſevere Cuts, he grapled with <hi>Dareill,</hi> and violently wreſting his Sword out of his hand, flung him from him again with ſuch force, as mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his bones ſhake within him; and ſo furiouſly charged upon <hi>Bragwell</hi> before the other could recover, that he not only obliged him to give back, but made the Blood run fearfully about his Ears. <hi>Dareill</hi> ſeeing his Companion in this plight, and himſelf without any weapon, runs to the Stile, and pulls from thence a Bar, with which he came behind <hi>Hawkwood,</hi> and gave him ſuch a blow e're he could turn about to receive him, as made him bend with one knee to the ground; but ſuddenly recovering him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, he was not long unrevenged; for being by this more and more in raged, he laid ſo hard upon <hi>Dareill,</hi> (the other be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng already faint for loſs of blood) that he made him fall as dead at his feet; and then charging upon the other, who was ſtaggering to the relief of his Companion, inflicted on him ſo many freſh wounds, that he likewiſe dropped, and with a faint voice cryed out for Mercy: So that <hi>Hawkwood,</hi> by the fearful wounds he had given them, ſuppoſing they were no longer men of this World, and finding himſelf hurt, threw down the bloody Sword, leaſt by bearing it away, the matter might be diſcovered; and bidding them beware how they baſely and ingloriouſly attempted to turn <hi>Aſſaſſins</hi> for the future, (tho' at the ſame time he verily believed they were never more capable of it) he purſued his way, penſive and thought<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of many things, but eſpecially of what had befell him; and ſoon concluded by what he had gathered (as I ſaid) from ſome words they had let fall, that it hapned through <hi>Gaſpero</hi>'s procurement; but thinking himſelf ſufficiently revenged, he reſolved to conceal the matter; and ſo coming home, and pretending wearineſs and indiſpoſition, he got him to Bed, having firſt provided materials to dreſs the hurts he had received.</p>
               <p>Long had not <hi>Hawkwood</hi> been in Bed, but the Servant-Maid (who came to bring him a Cawdle, and to enquire how he did) told him, That a Neighbours Boy, who had been at the Fair, had brought the ſad News of two mens being murthered in the Fields; and <hi>I'le warrant you,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>it has been done by ſome damn'd Rogues or other, for their money; and it was well</hi> Iohn, (ſaid ſhe, looking earneſtly upon our Youngſter, for whom ſhe had no ſmall affection) <hi>that you eſcaped their hands, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you came home ſo late. It was ſo,</hi> replyed he; and thereupon ſhewing much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to ſleep, (though indeed he had other matters to think on) ſhe left him. And now being alone, he began to think of what he had done, as alſo what would become of him, if it was known; <hi>Although</hi> (thought he) <hi>Heaven knows I fought in my own defence, to ſave my life; yet having no w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tneſs on Earth to prove it, (ſhould revenge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> Gaſpero, <hi>who will undoubtedly hear of what had hapned, bring the matter to a Tryal) it will aſſuredly go hard with me. But how</hi> (then replyed he again to himſelf) <hi>can he prove it? Yes, ſurely my being abroad late, by the ſelf-ſame way I took, which many th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t knew me we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l noted; and above all, if I am ſearched, by the wounds I ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e received, which will anſwer the weapons found by the dead Bodies. But then again, may I not plead my in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ocence and juſtifie the Fact? Alas! alas! truſt not, fond man, too much to that; Might and Clamour in ſo doubtful a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> may overbear even Innocence it ſelf. Well, what then is to be done? Why, only to avoid the Danger by ſlight. Ah! but then</hi> Dorinda <hi>muſt be left. Why, what
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:99890:11"/> of her? She ſcorns thy ſervice, rejects thy Love; yet in the beholding of her lovely Eyes there is ſome pleaſure, and in Hope there is a glimmering of Joy. VVell, but conſider again, that to come to a diſgraceful end, though undeſerved end, will not only divorce me from</hi> Dorinda, <hi>but bring a reproach upon my Relations. Fly th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n, fly, I ſay, and reſerve your ſelf for a better Fortune.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus the penſive <hi>Hawkwood</hi> having debated with himſelf, paſſed over the reſtleſs night till the morning dawned, when getting up, he packed up ſuch Neceſſaries as he thought convenient; together with the money he had got by his obliging behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, during his Service, that he might be gone with the firſt opportunity; the which whilſt he was doing, he heard the People tune their diſcourſe to the bloody Dialect of Murther, and horridly exclaim againſt the Murtherers, deſiring nothing more, than that they might be taken, proteſting Hanging was too good for them, and deviſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves a Thouſand ways to diſpatch them, when found: <hi>Ah!</hi> ſays one, <hi>they were bloody-minded Villains I'le warrant ye. Ay,</hi> ſays another, <hi>or elſe they would have been contented with the poor Mens money, and not have robbed them of Life and Money too. Alas!</hi> continued a third, <hi>and perhaps of ſomething elſe that was more precious; for I'le warrant ye, theſe poor men were in drink, (God bleſs us) and men in drink, ye know Neighbours, are not in a ſit condition to dye.</hi> Then by a croſs Wind comes in another, and with a ſhrill tone cries, <hi>Ay, but Neighbours, conſider, conſider, I ſay, their poor Wives and Children, what a Taking they will be in when they hear of this ſad misfortune; alas! my Heart e'en bleeds to think on't.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our Youngſter hearing theſe and the like diſcourſes, although he was before but wavering about his departure, (ſo much did <hi>Dorinda's</hi> love conſtrain him) is now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved upon it; and thereupon, that the conſternation of the Family may be leſſen'd about his departure, (for he intends to acquaint no body with it by word of mouth) he wrote the following Lines, and put them through the Key-hole of <hi>Dorinda</hi>'s Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, not doubting but they by that means wou'd come to her fair hands; and to her diſcretion he left it, whether ſhe would communicate them to any other, for ſo much he ſignified as a Superſcription: The Lines, I ſay, were theſe:
<q>
                     <l>NEeds muſt the man be gone that cannot ſtay,</l>
                     <l>The man whom Fate and Fortune drives away.</l>
                     <l>Ask not the cauſe, fair Maid, you know in part,</l>
                     <l>'Tis you have caus'd the Wounds that makes me ſmart:</l>
                     <l>Your Cruelty, your being too unkind,</l>
                     <l>Has wounded me in Body and in Mind.</l>
                     <l>Yet ſcarcely can you gueſs for what I go,</l>
                     <l>Though Time in Bloody Lines the Cauſe may ſhow;</l>
                     <l>And whilſt I range the World, the news may fly</l>
                     <l>Into your Ears with an unwelcome Cry:</l>
                     <l>That I in my defence that blood have ſpilt,</l>
                     <l>That wou'd with me more cruelly have dealt,</l>
                     <l>And leave you Judge whoſe was the greater Guilt.</l>
                     <l>Your Cauſe it was in the Original,</l>
                     <l>That did create the bold <hi>Aſſaſſins</hi> fall.</l>
                     <l>The love of you occaſion'd what is done;</l>
                     <l>For which remember me now I am gone:</l>
                     <l>Me, who through Fate, through Death, and Dangers wad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</l>
                     <l>For you moſt fair, and yet moſt cruel Maid.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:99890:12"/>
               <p>He needed not ſubſcribe it, for ſhe very well knew his hand: Nor did his wiſh in part fail him; for when ſhe came to unlock her Chamber-door, eſpying the Paper, ſhe took it up, and read it, wondering what it ſhould mean. But whilſt ſhe was pauſing, news was brought her, that <hi>Hawkwood</hi> was miſſing, and that he had been met ſome Miles out of Town, with a Bundle under his Arm; which had bred no ſmall wonder in the Family, in conſideration, that upon the ſearching of his Trunks, they found he had taken with him many things, the which, if he intended to return in any convenient time, (at leaſt) he would not have done: Nor could the Maid, who brought this word, and entirely loved him, though her modeſty had all along concealed it, refrain from Tears in the Relation. And now the fair <hi>Dorinda</hi> too plainly gueſſed at the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Lines, though ſhe knew nothing particularly of what had lately befallen him. And ſo leaving <hi>Hawkwood</hi> on his way, and the Family in wonder and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſternation at his ſudden departure, I ſhall return to the two Deſperadoes that I late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly left for dead.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How upon the Bruit of a Murther divers perſons haſted to the Field, tho' before they came, the two Ruffians recovering, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re got from thence; when killing by the way a Sheep, and taking out his Heart, they made <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſpero</hi> believe it was <hi>Hawk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood</hi>'s, whom they ſaid they had murthered: With other things, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>IT ſeems, a little after <hi>Hawkwood</hi> had left <hi>Dareill</hi> and <hi>Bragwell</hi> deſtitute (as he thought) of recovery, (for the one he imagined already dead, and the other expiring) a Youth came by, and ſeeing them in that condition, together with the blood that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured the ground, affrighted at ſo ghaſtly a ſight, he fled to the Town, and reported what he had ſeen, but for ſome time could not gain belief, the Peo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le telling him they might be ſome drunken men, who came from the Fair, fallen aſleep, and that having diſgorged their ſtomachs, he by the imperfect light, took it for Blood; but he conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affirming the contrary, and repeating their words and groans, at laſt ſo far pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed, that divers undertook to go with him to the place: And upon this Youth's report it was, that thoſe that I have mentioned grounded their diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>Divers (as I ſaid before) undertaking to go with the Youth, it ſo happened, that when they came there, they found not the men he ſpoke of, but there was the Bar of the Stile beſmeared with Blood, and much Blood lying on the ground; ſo that by plain ſymptomes the ſigns of Murther appearing, they concluded, that there had been ſome perſons murther'd, and upon ſecond thoughts, imagined they might be Thieves, and their Companions for fear of diſcovery (after the departure of thoſe that killed them) had carried off the dead Bodies, and either buried them in the Fields, or hid them in ſome Ditch or Hedge; whereupon they made a long and fruitleſs ſearch, till late in the morning: So that not returning home ſo ſoon as was expected, the old Women concluded upon the truth of the matter, which occaſion'd the diſcourſe under <hi>Hawkwood</hi>'s W ndow, which much contributed to his departure; though in the end his Name was thereby raiſed high as a Piramide; which in the ſequel of the Hiſtory will appear.</p>
               <p>Now ſome may demand what beca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of the wounded men, and what News <hi>Gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pero</hi> received of this Adventure? To which I anſwer, That being come to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and fearing not only a diſcovery of the buſineſs, but being in equal fear for <hi>Hawkwood,</hi> or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ather more (by being on the unjuſter ſide) than he for them, they made as good a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hift as they could to get away, were gone ſo far before they were enquired for, that thoſe who came in ſearch of them cou d not find them, and in the deplorable
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:99890:12"/> condition they were in, fell to conſulting with each other, how they ſhould ſhew their Faces to <hi>Gaſpero,</hi> ſeeing they had promiſed ſo much and performed ſo little; and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, if he come to know of their Treatment, how they ſhould come by their further Reward: Many ways they propoſed; but at length eſpying Sheep grazing by the light of the Moon, in the next Field, they reſolved to kill one of them, and take out his Heart, which they would make <hi>Gaſpero</hi> believe was that of <hi>Hawkwood,</hi> whom they had killed and privately buried. But then another queſtion aroſe, how they ſhould come off about their wounds, ſeeing if they had been really ſo valiant as they propoſed, it could not be reaſonably expected, that one man could have uſed them at that rate: But to ſalve this, they likewiſe concluded to inform him, That having done the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploit, and coming late through many by-ways, to prevent purſuit or diſcovery, they were ſet upon by Nine or Ten Robbers, who (from behind a Hedge) fell upon them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were aware; but as ſoon as they faced about and charged them, they fled, ſome with the loſs of an Arm, others miſerably hacked and wounded.</p>
               <p>Thus having contrived to delude the Old Man, theſe pretended Heroes turned their valour to the deſtruction of a harmleſs Sheep, and taking out of his Body what they wanted, they haſted to <hi>Gaſpero</hi>'s Houſe, the which (having well waſhed their wounds, and put themſelves in the beſt order they could) they reached by that it was day-light; when upon their knocking at the Gate, the Boy peeping through the Wicket, and perceiving their Hair ſtarch'd together, as it were, with blood, their Viſages pale and wan, with ſome Scars and Cuts upon them, their Garments rent, and many other ſigns of diſorder, he ran up to his Maſter, and (being an awkward Country Youth) told him, That the <hi>Redſhanks</hi> and <hi>Wild-Iriſh</hi> were at the Gate, and had brought <hi>Raw-head</hi> and <hi>Bloody-bones</hi> along with them: Such fooliſh Fables (by way of deſcription) it ſeems his Mother had put into his Head, to bugbear him in his Infancy; and ſo much he fancied theſe men to be like what he had heard, that he could not be induced to go down again to enquire their buſineſs, tho' they ſtill ſtood knock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with much earneſtneſs, as aſhamed to be diſcovered by any in the poſture they were in: Nor did <hi>Gaſpero</hi>'s fears poſſeſs him (upon the relation the Boy had made) with any thing elſe, but that they had brought <hi>Hawkwood</hi> dead, or ſorely wounded, along with them, to bury, or otherwiſe diſpoſe of him in his Houſe; whereupon he conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, if it was ſo, he would neither admit them, or own that he knew them, or had ſet them on work, for fear himſelf ſhould be charged with the Murther; but going up, peeping out of the window of the Lodge, &amp; perceiving the contrary, he deſcended again, and opened the Gate; yet at the ſight of his <hi>Janizaries</hi> he was not a little amazed, and they on the other hand complained of their ſtanding there too long, which (they ſaid) had they been purſued, might have been a means to have diſcovered the whole In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treague: But waving further diſcourſe, he carried them into a private Room, and fetched divers Cordials, and other refreſhments, to revive them, whom he found, by the faultering of their ſpeech, faint, and almoſt ſpent; and after they had taken ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral luſty ſwigs, ſo that their ſpirits came (as it were) again, he began to enquire of the ſucceſs of the Enterprize: To whom <hi>Dareill</hi> replyed; As for that, or any thing elſe in that or the like nature, that he or his Companion undertook, he need not fear the ſucceſs; for they were not wont to make Childrens Shoes of their buſineſs, but to perform it through-ſtitch: <hi>As for him who lately put the Affront upon you, you may</hi> (continued he) <hi>be well aſſured, he will never do the like again. Nay, if he do,</hi> (ſays <hi>Bragwell,</hi> pulling the Sheeps Heart out of his Pocket, and holding it up) <hi>then this is none of his. Ay, ay,</hi> ſays <hi>Dareill, if he do Brother, that is none of his: But as ſure as that is an Heart,— Mark ye me Sir— How!</hi> (ſays <hi>Gaſpero,</hi> interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:99890:13"/> him) <hi>and, Have you murther'd him? I wou'd not for any thing have had you done ſo: How! murther'd him! Is it poſſible? Poſſible,</hi> replys <hi>Dareill, alack, alack, very eaſie with us that are uſed to it: But this, indeed, (becauſe you injoyned us to the contrary) was not with our Wills. No indeed,</hi> ſaid <hi>Bragwell, it was not with our good-Wills, but by chance; f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r thinking to ſtrike him with the flat, to crack his Crown, or ſo, by an unfortunate ſlip of my Back-Sword, I whipp'd off his Head before I was aware, and that I would have brought you, were it not too cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſom; but this may ſatisfie any reaſonable man of the Truth of it; for unleſs he have two hearts and two heads, with a Needle and Thread to ſew himſelf up again, he's no more a man of this World. And what,</hi> ſaid <hi>Gaſpero, have you done with him? What if the Body ſhould be found? Fear not that,</hi> ſaid <hi>Dareill, for we have laid him up to the Reſurrection, with ſuch an heap of Earth and Stones upon him, that an Earthquake can't remove him. Well,</hi> ſaid <hi>Gaſpero, this is more than I bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain'd with you for; though, being done, 'tis paſt recovery. But how came you</hi> (continued he) <hi>thus hurt Gentlemen?</hi> To which laſt queſtion they replyed, as they had before determined, <hi>viz.</hi> How nine or ten well-armed Thieves burſt out of an Ambuſh upon them, and had given them thoſe wounds before they could prepare or put themſelves in a poſture of Defence; but they afterward had not only put them to flight, but pepper'd them off in ſuch a manner, that they doubted not, that although they had ſo much ſtrength as to fly from the place, yet that ſome of them were by this time in the condition of <hi>Hawkwood.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gaſpero</hi> being thus far ſatisfied, and taking all they ſaid for granted, immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fetched them Balms, Salves, and Oyntments, helping them to dreſs their wounds, and appointed them a private Apartment, with all manner of Neceſſaries, till they ſhould be recovered, with an intent then to diſmiſs them with ſuch Rewards as might charm them into ſilence.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X. </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Gaſpero</hi> packed away the Ruffians beyond the Seas; And how he was terrified with the Comical Adventure of a naked Wench, which he ſuppoſed to be <hi>Hawk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood</hi>'s Ghoſt; And many other pleaſant matters that befell on this occaſion.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>BY this time the two pretended Mirmidons being pretty well recovered, and much recruited with good Dyet, <hi>Gaſpero</hi> was deſirous to be rid of their company, leſt by words they might let fall, the ſuppoſed Murther ſhould come to light: But then he conſidered, if they were abroad, and hankered thereabout, it might be the ſame thing; and therefore, what to do in this caſe, he found himſelf at a loſs; but conſidering ſomething muſt be done, he at laſt came to a concluſion: That if they were ſent beyond the Seas, his fears would by their abſence be removed; and about this he reſolved to confer with them, not deſpairing to have it done with their own liking, for that he found their fortune was as good in one place as another; and to have it better'd by a good Sum of Money, in a diſtant Country, might be acceptable. Nor (as Luck would have it) did they leſs jump in quill; for juſt as he was debating this matter with himſelf, they came down to him, and beſought him that he would diſmiſs them, for that conſidering all the circumſtances that attended the Intreague, their long tarriance in his Houſe might breed a ſuſpition; and that, although they were very ſeldome ſeen, yet one or other of the Servants might ſcatter words that mig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t diſcover them; and ſeeing they were men of Fortune, if he could ſet them
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:99890:13"/> over Sea, ſo that when they came there, they might have ſomething to ſubſiſt on, till they had opportunity to recruit, it would do very well. This was on both hands agreed on, without any further controverſie; and they making a vow never to return, unleſs forced to it by ſome extraordinary accident, he gave them (to be ſure that they ſhould go) a Bill to receive Fifty <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Dollers, at <hi>Bruxelles,</hi> in one of the <hi>Flemiſh</hi> Provinces, and ſomewhat to bear their Charges by the way; and ſo packing them on board an outward-bound Ship, he bid his two Champions farewel.</p>
               <p>Thus (as he ſuppoſed) being revenged, and freed from all fear of diſcovery, he began to carreſs himſelf in his ſecurity; yet ſometimes, when he reflected on the imagined Tranſaction, he found a damp upon his Spirits, but moſtly in the night, for through multitude of buſineſs in the day he was diverted from it; but in the end a Comical accident fell out, that overwhelmed him with a thouſand fears; &amp; was in this manner:</p>
               <p>It ſo happened, that <hi>Gaſpero</hi> having a pleaſant Orchard, or Garden, belonging to his Houſe, and it being in Autumn when the pregnant Earth produces the effects of her teeming labour in their full perfection; the <hi>Douvigha,</hi> or Governante, (for ſo I may properly call the old Woman, who was his Houſe-keeper) hearing her Daughter, a plump red-headed wench, was to be married to a jolly blade, a Coachman, her fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-Servant, ſhe ſent in the Evening for her, when <hi>Gaſpero</hi> was gone abroad; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to give her Inſtructions, or to what other purpoſe, I leave to the conſtruction of the Reader; but however, that ſhe might be more charming to her Bridegroom, ſhe admoniſhed her to go to the Spring in the Orchard, (or rather, for its pleaſantneſs, might be termed a Fountain) and there to waſh her ſelf, directing her to unſtrip her ſelf, and leave her Clothes in an Arbor a little beyond it. The Wench took this for a kind of an odd Prank; but her Mother, for many weighty reaſons, urging it, and ſhe being favoured by the light of the Moon, no longer diſputed her Commands, who promiſed to watch the mean while, that no body ſhould come in at the Garden-Gate to interrupt her, the Boy being gone out with his Maſter; and as for any other Invaſions, ſhe doubted not, but the walls would ſecure her againſt them; and ſo ſhe proceeded to do what ſhe was commanded.</p>
               <p>Now it ſo unluckily fell out, that a young fellow of the Town, having by the help of a Ladder gotten over the Wall, to poſſeſs himſelf of ſome of the delicate Fruit that grew in the Orchard, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> was at that very Iuncture gotten upon a Tree that hung over the Spring, with its ſpreading branches laden with Fruits, rin'd with Vermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion and Gold; or, as the Poet has it, in Relation to the Garden of the <hi>Heſperides:</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>With Golden Fruits the laden Boughs did bend;</l>
                     <l>On whom a wakeful Dragon did attend. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Now whether the Fellow, who perceived the Laſs approaching, had this whim in his Head, to fancy her the Dragon that kept the Orchard, I ſubmit it to the Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Reader. But if this ſtory be true, (as I would not have you doubt it, ſeeing it is in Print) he lay ſnug upon one of the branches, not only till ſhe unclad her ſelf, but when ſhe entred timerouſly by degrees, as either by reaſon of her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing a ſtranger to the place, or fearing the depth, (being no great Artiſt, I ſupp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e, at ſwimming on her Face) or that ſhe meant thereby not to cool all at once; but in the end growing bolder, ſhe fell (the better to make quick-work on't) to daſhing ſpat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, dabbling, and ſcrubbing her ſelf at a ſtrange rate: When (O the danger of too much curioſity!) our Youngſter in the Clouds reaching his Head too low, (upon what account is doubtful, tho' ſome may be apt to gueſs it was out of humility, by this time
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:99890:14"/> fancying her to be <hi>Diana</hi>) he lets go his hold, and down he drops, Apples and all; giving a daſh as great as <hi>Jupiter</hi>'s Logg, whom <hi>Aeſop</hi> tells us, was thrown to the Frogs, together with the further account he gives of it in his Fable, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This ſudden noiſe not only troubled the Waters, but made the Laſs (like a River-Nymph, with dropping Hair, diſorderly hanging, ſome on her Breaſts, and ſome on her Shoulders) haſte thence, &amp; unmindful (through ſudden fear) of returning for her Clothes, in her native Livery of Nakedneſs, ſpring out of the Fountain, and with ſpeed (not inferiour to <hi>Attalanta</hi>) haſte to the Houſe for ſhelter. Now, as if Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief had this Night ſet all her Engines on work, the old Woman had juſt let in <hi>Gaſpero,</hi> who (having ſent his Foot-Boy about further buſineſs) was returned alone; and had ſcarce entred the Hall-door, and about to ſhut it, but in burſt the Wench upon him, and with the violence overthrew him, where he lay crying out for help; whilſt our Governante (to colour the buſineſs the better) letting her Candle drop, (as you muſt ſuppoſe, through fear, though indeed to hide her Daughters naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, till ſhe eſcaped into ſome corner of the Houſe, for further relief): Whilſt the Governante, I ſay, having dropped her Candle, came to his relief, and by woful ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, upon enquiry, found that his Guts (by reaſon of the fright this Apparition put him into) were fallen very low in his Breeches; and further, that not only a deadly paleneſs had covered his Face, but he was taken with ſuch a fit of trembling, that his Ioints ſeemed of no more uſe to ſupport him, than if they had been made of a Quaking Pudding: Nor could ſhe in a long time (though ſhe ſtrove what in her lay) bring him to his right Wits; and when that Little Senſe he had left was returned, he ſtill trembled, and with a gnaſhing of his Teeth, and a wild kind of a Countenance, deſired to be conveyed to a Couſin's Houſe of his, not far diſtant from his own; charging her withal, upon her Life, not to ſay any thing of what ſhe had ſeen.</p>
               <p>Glad of this opportunity was our <hi>Douvignia,</hi> that ſhe might in time return to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire into, and calm her Daughters fears, who (poor Wench) ſtood ſhivering and ſhaking on the Stair-head, as not being capable of entering any of the Chambers, by reaſon of their being locked: Nor ſtayed ſhe, after <hi>Gaſpero</hi> was ſafely lodged in the hands of his Friends; but leaving him to make his Apology for perfuming the Houſe, ſhe abruptly took her leave; and coming home, ſtruck a Light, where ſhe found the poor Girl, as aforeſaid, who revealed to her all that happened, intreating her to fetch her Clothes, and ſuffer her ſpeedily to depart; which ſhe accordingly did; the Fellow (before her coming) having ſcrambled out of the Water, and recovered (by the help of his Ladder) the other ſide of the Wall; but by leaving (for haſte) his Bag of Apples behind him, that plainly demonſtrated the purpoſe of his coming. This, upon her Mothers returning with the Clothes, the Daughter was informed, and ſoon after became ſatisfied; though at firſt ſhe imagined it to be no leſs than the Prince of the Air turned Madg-howlet, who ſuppoſing her (at a diſtance) to be a Sea-pye, or young Duckling, had ſtooped to make her his Prey. But being again clad, and diſmiſſed, ſhe vowed, if her Husband was not contented with the white<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of her skin, he ſhould ſcrub it himſelf with his Horſe-Cloth; for ſhe'd venture no more by Moon-light on that occaſion.</p>
               <p>The old Woman having diſmiſſed her Daughter with Motherly Advice, rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to Marriage-af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>airs, and the Boy being by this time come to keep houſe, ſhe returned to her former Charge, by the way framing an excuſe for her abſence; (as who doubts, but w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m n have t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>em at their fingers ends on all occaſions, eſpecially Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants) As for he that doubts this, let me tell him by the way, it will be hardly worth
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:99890:14"/> his while to give himſelf an experimental ſatisfaction, the matter being ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gaſpero</hi> by this time being pretty well recovered, and having refreſhed himſelf, was perſwaded to go home, but he would by no means hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ken to it, fancying (it ſeems) that this naked Laſs was no other than the Ghoſt of <hi>Hawkwood,</hi> imagining in that conſternation, that the red Hair that hung in Rats-tails, by reaſon of its being wet, to be the bloody Cuts and Slaſhes that had been given to diſpatch him. Such powerful effects have fear to delude the Eyes and Senſes; though it might probably happen, that (to heighten the deluſion) the Laſs might through the ſame effect of fear, be reduced to a Ghoſtly paleneſs: But however, the old Woman being ſilent, for her Daughters credit, and not attempting to convince him of the miſtake, his ſickly fancy preſented ſuch Ideas for the future, that he ſoon removed (to the no ſmall wonder of the Inhabitants, who knew not the cauſe) from that Houſe, though a very pleaſant Seat, to another in a diſtant Village, and there continued for a while in much Antiety; but the Ghoſt appearing no more, he by degrees was recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to himſelf: Where I ſhall leave him, and return to young <hi>Hawkwood;</hi> from whom (for the better contexture and pleaſantneſs of Hiſtory in this kind) I have been too long abſent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Dorinda,</hi> and the whole Family, were much troubled at the ſudden departure of <hi>Hawkwood:</hi> And how he coming to an Inn on the Road, hears the Relation and Adventure of a blind Race; undertakes to lye in a haunted Chamber, and takes the ſuppoſed Ghoſt Priſoner, and is well rewarded for his pains.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THe Maſter of <hi>Hawkwood,</hi> and the whole Family, (the fair <hi>Dorinda</hi> not excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) being much troubled at his ſudden departure, ſent divers Meſſengers after him, but they either miſſing the Road he went, or being too ſlow, returned no wiſer than they went; and being unſucceſsful in this, they began to gueſs at the reaſon of his going away; but though there were many Arguments, <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con,</hi> yet all came ſhort of the true reaſon; but <hi>Dorinda,</hi> who indeed underſtood ſome part of it, tho ſcarcely the main buſineſs, yet w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at ſhe knew, (for fear of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lame in not ſooner re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealing it) ſhe kept it to her ſelf: But moſt of all, the Maid (who hoped to gain his Love by her good Services) lamented his abſence.</p>
               <p>Whilſt this concern for <hi>Hawkwood</hi>'s abſence was at home, he was trudging the Road, or wandring through the unfrequented Woods, the better to avoid purſuit, till at length (weary and faint) he ſate him down, and began to lament his misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune; but moſt of all, that he muſt be baniſhed from the ſight of fair <hi>Dorinda; O!</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>that this days Sun ſees me ſo unhappy, to forgo all that is dear to me on Earth!</hi> But having vented his ſorrow in ſighs and ſuch-like expreſſions, he began to be more moderate, and recollect his manly ſpirits, to fortifie his Reaſon, that ſo, whatever befell him, he might with Fortitude and Patience ſupport himſelf. But having by this time travelled far, and night coming on, he bethought himſelf of a place to repoſe in; and having a pleaſant Town in Proſpect, he haſted thither, and took up in the chief Inn, which was not large, being only a Country Village; yet not doubting of a Lodging, he ſate him down, and called for what the Houſe afforded, and ſo ſtayed till much within night before he asked whether he might lye there or no; when calling his Landlady, he put the queſtion to her, who ſhaking her Head,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:99890:15"/> told him, That indeed they had a ſpa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Room, with a Bed in it, but to deal plainly with him, there had been for ſome nights paſt a great diſturbance there, by the forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly throwing things up and down, and that ſhe could conclude no other from thence, than that it was haunted with ſome evil Spirit; and for that reaſon, ſhe being a Widow-Woman, and many times none but her ſelf and her Maid in the Houſe, was about to leave it.</p>
               <p>At the ſeriouſneſs of this Diſcourſe, delivered withal with ſuch earneſtneſs, <hi>Hawkwood</hi> could not chooſe but ſmile; at which the Hoſteſs ſeemed a little angry, imagining he laughed at her, as if ſhe had told him a Fable; but he bid her be paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, telling her, that ſeeing it Rained, (as indeed it did) and was a very ſtormy night, rather than he would be deſtitute of a Lodging, he would venture (with her leave) to take up in that Room. <hi>Nay,</hi> (ſaid ſhe, taking him up haſtily) <hi>ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e a care young-man, what you ſay: for I vow and proteſt, I would not have any Body come to any harm in my Houſe for all the World; for</hi> (continued ſhe) <hi>the noiſe is ſo ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible about Twelve of the Clock, or ſomewhat after, that the ſtouteſt of our Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riers (though you ſee they are great Lubbarly fellows) dare not venture into the Room; Nay, one of them did but juſt put his Snout in, and had a ſtone thrown at him, which beat him down Stairs, and ſo mawled him, that he lay by it three days.</hi> By this <hi>Hawkwood</hi> (who was of a prompt wit) verily conceited it muſt be ſome trick put upon the Houſe; for he conſidered, that the Devil ſeldome or never carries ſtones in his Pocket, by reaſon he alwaies leaves his Breeches at home (if ever he wears any, as ten to one he does not); and thereupon reſted the better ſatisfied, promiſing not to refuſe that Bed at any rate. But whilſt they were thus diſcourſing, in comes a great Lubbarly fellow, laughing till his ſides cracked again; and being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded what was the occaſion, could not ſpeak for proceeding in his Laughter; but in the end growing a little calmer, ſaid, That he had been at the running of a blind Race: And when they deſired him to expound his Meaning, he ſaid, That blind <hi>Tom,</hi> a fellow well known in the Town, had laid a Wager with another that could ſee, to run with him a Mile; but with <hi>Proviſo,</hi> that himſelf ſhould name the Time and Place, and the other to be ready at an houres warning, whenever the blind man ſhould require it. <hi>Now,</hi> ſays he, <hi>you may think this ſomewhat ſtrange; but you ſhall hear how it happened. The blind man, you'l ſay, being as capable of ſeeing in ſo dark a Night as this is, as the other, called him out, about an hour and a half ſince, to run down the</hi> Green-Lane, <hi>where (you muſt know) there are divers miry Sloughs; ſome good fellows that ſided with blind</hi> Tom, <hi>laying Cart-Ropes from Hedge to Hedge, and holding either end on the inſide of the Banks, on the brink of the Sloughs, when he that had Eyes came foremoſt, they, with a ſudden jerk, whipt up his Heels, and tumbled him over Head and Heels in the Mire; yet not well un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding how the Accident h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ppened, the firſt bout, up he gets, and haſtens on to the ſecond Slough, where he was ſerved in the like nature, and then diſcovered the miſchief, by the laughing of thoſe behi d the Hedge; and ſo (fearful to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed any further, for fear of breaking his Neck) all bemired, he ſcrambled up into the Field, and let the blind man p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſs on to win he Wager: And nothing vexes me, but that they were ſuch Blockhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ds to laugh; for had they not done it, ten to one, the fellow would have concluded, the Spirit that haun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s your Houſe, had been abroad, and conjured up his Heels.</hi> Vpon this the Bumpkin ſet up a laughing again, as if he would have burſt the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iſt-band of his breeches. And although the Hoſteſſes mouth ſtood almoſt a quart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r of an hour at half-cock, to tell him what <hi>Hawkwood</hi> had propoſed, yet could ſhe not be heard till his laughter was ended; but
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:99890:15"/> then giving ear to what ſhe ſaid, he greatly diſapproved his reſolution, laying before him the dangerous conſequence, and telling him a world of ſtories of Spirits, Witches, Fairies, <hi>Robin Good-fellows,</hi> and the like; the which when <hi>Hawkwood</hi> began to doubt, in relation to the Truth, he quoted the Famous Hiſtory of Dr. <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus,</hi> the Play of the <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> Witches, the penny Book of the <hi>Fairy</hi> Pranks, and the Ballad of <hi>Robin Good-fellow,</hi> vowing he had ſeen them all in Print, and wondred that any body would queſtion the truth of 'em: <hi>But it may be, friend,</hi> (continued he to <hi>Hawkwood) you are not ſo deep learned, nor ſo great a Scholar as I am, and therefore have none of theſe Books in your Library.</hi> At this <hi>Hawkwood</hi> could not forbear ſmiling, and with his ſilence ſeem to give conſent to what he afterward ſaid, for he ſtaid not long, being called away to participate of the Wager. And now bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time being come, tho' many perſwaſions were uſed by the Hoſteſs, and others, to avert him from lying in that Room, yet he uſed ſuch Arguments, that he made them reſt ſatisfied, that (if he was not a Conjurer, as ſome of them vainly conjectured him) he was a man that had been converſant in ſuch matters, and was not afraid of Spirits: And ſo furniſhing himſelf with a good Battoon, and a dark Lanthorn, with a watch Candle in it, up Stairs he goes, and takes poſſeſſion of the Chamber, laying him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf down on the bed in his Clothes, and ſetting the things I have mentioned by him; whilſt the Hoſteſs and the reſt were Croſſing themſelves, and praying for his ſucceſs, the former proteſting upon her honeſty, that if he conjured down, or freed her Houſe from the Spirit, ſhe would give him all the money in her Purſe.</p>
               <p>Now ſo it happened, that about the uſual hour, that is ſomewhat after Twelve, as he was muſing on the matter, he heard ſomething about the Window; for note, it was an upper Room, which had a Glaſs Caſement, which went out into a Gutter, between two ridges of Houſes, and ſo into a Neighbours Houſe at a Window of the like nature. <hi>Hawkwood,</hi> as I ſaid, ſeeing this, reſolved (whatever it was) to let it enter without moleſtation, and thereupon lay as ſtill as a Mouſe in a Cheeſe; when by and by open flew the Caſement, and in with the Heels formoſt comes ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing all in whire, and began to tumble and throw the things about with a terrible noiſe; whereupon <hi>Hawkwood</hi> ſoftly rearing himſelf up, goes with his Lanthorn in one hand, and his Cudgel in the other, and coming as near as was convenient, opens his Lanthorn, which ſhining juſt in the face of the thing, where the Shroud covered it not, he plainly perceived it to be no other than the laughing Fellow, dreſſed up in <hi>Pimlico,</hi> as Painters fooliſhly Picture or fancy the ſhadow of a Ghoſt: At the ſight of the Light, the Fellow ſtarted back; but ſoon recovering himſelf, thought to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dare <hi>Hawkwood,</hi> whom indeed (as he afterward confeſſed) he little expected to find there, although he had heard him talk of it, but found himſelf miſtaken; for <hi>John</hi> ſtepping up to the Beard of him, ſaid, <hi>And have I caught ye?</hi> whereupon recoiling ſtill towards the window, with a feigned, yet lamentable voice, he ſaid, <hi>Mortal, come not near me, whoe'er thou art, leſt I deſtroy thee. Not near thee!</hi> ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted <hi>Hawkwood, wert thou him that I take thee not to be, I would approa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h thee.</hi> And with that he fell upon him with ſuch fury, that in vain he endeavour'd to retreat; for being a fat and unweildy fellow, in haſtily retiring, he ſtuck faſt in the Window, with his Breech innermoſt, which <hi>Hawkwood</hi> belaboured till he cryed out for Mercy, and then he dragged him in again by the Heels, and pulled the ſhroud over his Ears; whereupon the fellow looked ſo ſimply, that he could not find in his heart to give him any more rough uſage; but after paſſing ſome Ieſts upon him, for his ſimplicity, clap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing the Shroud about his Neck, opened the door, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d ſo lead him down ſtairs, like a Horſe in a Collar; which the Servant-Maid (who had liſtened
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:99890:16"/> with much fear during the ſcuffle) perceiving, runs down one pair of Stairs, and tumbles down another, to tell the people, who were aſſembled below in expectation of the iſſue, that the Lodger had taken the Devil Priſoner, with a great Ruff about his neck, &amp; was bringing him down amongſt them: Vpon theſe words of the wench, who delivered them with abrupt ſtammerings, and a frightful countenance, they were in a Quandary what to do, whether to ſtay or to flee the Houſe, for now they verily belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved young <hi>Hawkwood</hi> to be a Conjurer; but e're they could determine any thing, he entred the Room, with his Priſoner, whereat fome ſhuffled one way, and ſome another; but he calling to them, and bidding them not be afraid, for that no hurt would enſue to any, they recollected their ſcattering Senſes, and at laſt found him (who had been ſo long a terror to them) no other than their Neighbour at the next Houſe, ſo that their fear was turned into loud laughter: And the Man looking all this while like an <hi>Ignoramus,</hi> and enduring their gibes and taunts, ingenuouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, What he had done, was to make the Hoſteſs leave her Houſe, that it might fall into his hands; and for the Pranks he had played, he ſaid, he was well bumba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, and heartily ſorry, hoping that would make ſatisfaction; but <hi>Hawkwood,</hi> not content with this, commanded him to ask her forgiveneſs upon his Knees; which done, in token of reconciliation, he made them ſhake hands, and kiſs each other. And ſo that night being ſpent in merriment, the next morning (being highly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauded for his courage, and well rewarded for the diſcovery) he took his leave, and left the Hoſteſs in quiet poſſeſſion for the future.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII. </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Hawkwood</hi> having left the Inn, went on Shipboard, where he found one <hi>Lovewell,</hi> of the ſame Profeſſion, who gives him an account of his Birth; tells him the Tradition of St. <hi>Winifreds</hi> Well; relates his being put to the Gentle-Craft; and the ſtrange Adventure of a dead Man.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>HAwkwood, <hi>by his laſt nights Adventure, having encreaſed his ſtore, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by not only enabled, but encouraged to proceed, ſeeing in his early underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings Fortune had befriended him, reſolves (now he was on his way) to ſee other Lands, and ſo makes to the next Sea-Port, where he found a Ship ready to ſail, and having agreed with the Maſter committed himſelf to the Ocean.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now it ſo happened, that making his Profeſſion known, he found a dapper young fellow in the ſame Veſſel of the like Myſtery; and finding him expert and ingenious, with him he contracted ſuch familiarity, that afterwards they became almoſt inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Friends, and were ſucceſsful in many Adventures; as the Sequel will mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt.</p>
               <p>Hawkwood, <hi>I ſay, having met with a Companion of his Travels, who had almoſt been as ſtrangely croſſed by Fortune as himſelf, eſpecially in the buſineſs of Love, which in general he had told him, he imagined his happineſs encreaſed upon him: And now they being long at Sea, he made it his requeſt to him, that to paſs away the time till they could land at the firſt Forreign Port, he would give him a relation of ſome particulars that had paſſed, which he promiſed him,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>but to run them over at preſent as briefly as might be, by reaſon they might otherways prove too long for the Voyage, and by that he might be obliged to break off abruptly.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:99890:16"/>
               <p>I was <hi>(ſaid he)</hi> born in <hi>Flint-ſhire,</hi> at a place near St. <hi>Winifreds</hi> Well, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe called <hi>Holy-Well,</hi> ſo famouſly memorable for its frequent Viſitations, and the Cures it performs, and (as Tradition has it) ſprung up above a Thouſand Years ſince; where the Head of that Virgin was cut off by a <hi>Pagan</hi> Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce, from whom ſhe fled to ſave her Chaſtity; and ever ſince, the Red Stones in the bottom of it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are fancyed as a laſting Memory to her Name and Sanctity, to bear the Tincture of her Blood. Here, I ſay, being born, and chriſten'd by the Name of <hi>Francis Love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> through the care of a tender Mother, I ſoon grew up, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d being at convenient years, was ſent to an Uncle of mine, who profeſſed the Gentle-Craft in <hi>London;</hi> but although he was Rich, he was ſo penurious, that I had not been there a week before I began to miſs my Mothers Cupboard (my Father being now dead); for being barred of my Belly-Timber, and kept ſhort ſo ſoon, I began to think that worſe might follow; for our Family conſiſted of no more than my Uncle, an old Wench, and my ſelf; and working privately, we lived in a dark ſmoaky Alley, over which a diſcouraging Cloud of Night hung, even in the midſt of Day, ſo that we ſeemed to live in miſts and ſhades; yet were up early and late; the Old Man taking eſpecial care, that his Couſin ſhould not be idle; ſo that in a ſmall time, with making up Wax, and drawing the Ends, I ſmelt worſe than a Tarpawlin: Nor could I have a ſweet breath, for Onions and toaſted Cheeſe was the greateſt part of our Dyet; which my Uncle extolled above any other Proviſion; only on <hi>Sundays</hi> we were allowed a Butter'd Pudding; but as if Eggs, Plumbs, and Suet, had been as great Strangers in <hi>London,</hi> as in the Deſarts of <hi>Arabia,</hi> when we ſought for any of them, we were forced to return them, like a broken Citizen, <hi>Non eſt inventus:</hi> And though I had contrived to ſurprize or ſtorm the Cupboard, I had not mended my Markets; for indeed my Uncle was ſo kind (however he fared abroad I know not) never to exceed us in our Dyet; and I the rather believe he did it, to encourage us to be valiant againſt the Tyrant <hi>Famine.</hi> By this means, and often faſting, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came lean, and out of order; I complained indeed, but my complaints were only anſwered, It was the Faſhion of the Town to live ſparingly; ſo that, when at any time I got a Penny for carrying home a pair of Shoes, I fancied my ſelf as rich as <hi>Croeſus,</hi> making it ſerve me for two mornings draughts, at half a pint a time; for our Drink at home was no better than our Victuals, not One in Twenty by the taſte being able to diſtinguiſh it from Water. Thus, for three Months, I lived a kind of an impatient life, every day expecting my Mothers coming up, that I might have my Dyet mended, or be removed. But whilſt I was in this expectation, one Evening being ſent to a Cuſtomer with a pair of ſhoes, I met a Coffin, with divers in Mourning following it, and amongſt the reſt, in a doleful tone, with wringing of hands, and many other expreſſions of ſorrow, I heard a woman cry out, O my dear Husband! how am I ſeparated from thee by cruel Deſtiny! whom I ſo much loved, who wert my Joy, my Hope, and all my Comfort in this World: Thou, alas! <hi>(conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued ſhe)</hi> art now going to a dark and gloomy Houſe, where is no joy, no pleaſure, no delight; to an Houſe where the ſound of Muſick is a ſtranger, and where thoſe dwell, that neither eat nor drink. Now I being but a Novice, and hearing this deſcription of the place, could (at that time) fancy it to be no other than my Uncles houſe; and therefore turning back again, I haſted home with all the ſpeed imaginable, and fell to knocking at the Door, as if I would have burſt it in pieces; my Uncle called to know who was there, but through the fear I was in that they ſhould arrive be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I could have the door open, I was incapable of reply; ſo that continuing my
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:99890:17"/> importunity, down he came, and began angrily to demand the reaſon of ſuch rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: O! Uncle, Uncle, (ſaid I, and thereupon fell to bolting and barrocading the Door, and ſetting my Back againſt it) the people are bringing a dead Man hither: Away you fool, ſaid he, what, Art thou mad? A dead Man! quoth a, pſha, pſha, thou ſimple boy, ſure thou art not ſo ſilly to believe it. Nay, nay Uncle, replyed I, I do believe it; for I am certain, I heard 'em ſay they were carrying him to a dark and ſorrowful houſe, where there was neither eating nor drinking; and therefore they can me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n no other, but This.</p>
               <p>At theſe words the old Man began to ſmile, yet ſcarcely knew whether he ought to be angry or pleaſed; yet in the end attributing it to my Simplicity, he by his ſophiſtry ſoon convinced me of my miſtake, and by that means removed my fear.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>At this Story</hi> Hawkwood <hi>could not refrain from ſmiling: But now the Cook giving notice by the ringing of a Bell, that Dinner was ready,</hi> Lovewell <hi>broke off his Diſcourſe, with a promiſe after their repaſt to proceed.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lovewell</hi> relates how he was met by a young Merchant-Taylor, who carried him to a ſplendid Feaſt, Annually held by the young Men of that Profeſſion, on St. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lielmus</hi> Day, in honour of that Saint, ſo much eſteemed by this Trade; And of the ſplendid Entertainment; And how he by that means came to be of the Trade.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſhort Repaſt being ended, (for long you muſt not expect it to continue in a place where Commons are ſhort, and Appetites exceeding large, ſo made by change of Air, and difference of the Climate)</hi> Hawkwood, <hi>deſirous to hear more of the Adventures of him whom he now had adopted his Companion, was not wanting to put</hi> Lovewell <hi>in mind of his Promiſe, nor he leſs ready to ſatisfie his expectation; whereupon he thus proceeded:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Long <hi>(ſaid he)</hi> I had not been with my Uncle of the Gentle Craft, after the ſtory I have mentioned, but growing weary of my Trade, (and more of my uſage) and my Mother not coming to Town, as I expected, it ſo happened: As one day <hi>I</hi> went abroad, and was walking the ſtreets, penſive and melancholly, I met with a dapper ſpruce fellow, who marking my Countenance, and by that gueſſing at the diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance of my mind, bearing up with me, began to enquire into my Country, Paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, Buſineſs in Town, and finally my Name, with many more things and matters, too tedious to recite; of all which I ſatisfied him as well as I could; but it ſeems he knew them before as well as my ſelf, happening in the ſequel to be my Country-man and Neighbour. This Youth invited me to go along with him; but I, who had been terrified both by my Mother and Uncle, with the fear of being Spirited, the dread of <hi>Bugby's-hole,</hi> ſo much wrought upon my conceit, that with ſuch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements as I had, I endeavour'd to excuſe his invitation, by pretending buſineſs, and want of leiſure: When indeed it was the ſame with St. <hi>Criſpin</hi>'s Day, the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Holy-day my Uncle had allow'd me ſince my coming to me, and in generoſity, for the ſake of that Saint, ſo much admired by the Trade, had gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en me Three-half-pence to ſpend as I thought convenient, though withal admoniſhing me by the by, to lay it out in good Liquor, tipping me the wink, that that was the beſt way
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:99890:17"/> to employ it: Now with this mighty Sum, and ſome other pence I had given me by Cuſtomers, I was going (you muſt know) to ſee a Country-man of mine; when in the end it happened to be the very Youth I had met as before, but ſo altered in his Clothes and Carriage, that I knew him not, (though I had heard where he lived) till he firſt diſcovered himſelf to me, and then we lovingly embraced each other, and (after the asking and anſwering many queſtions) I conſented to accompany him; and ſtra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ghtway he led me to a place, where I found a great number of young Sparks in the height of merriment, who every one, upon my entrance riſing from their reſpective ſeats, came and pay'd me a welcoming Complement. Now I, who knew not what all this ſhould mean, ſtood like an Owl amongſt the Jackdaws, and knew not what to ſay for my ſelf; but he that brought me thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her, ſupplyed my defect, and told them, I was an honeſt Country-man, though not of the ſame Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion: Then they demanded my Calling, which I frankly told them; upon which turning their Heads on one ſide, not utterly to daſh me out of countenance, they fell to ſn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ckering for a while, but afterward made me ſit down, and bid me heartily wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come; when on a ſudden, all the Tables were ſpread with ſuch ſtore of Varieties, that at the ſight thereof I ſtood gaping and gazing, as if I had been in another world; but recollecting my ſelf, and ſeeing others fall to, I made no bones to do the like, and there fed not as the Country Eſquire ordered his Man, for that day, or the morrow, but to ſupply the defect of many hungry Meals paſt, as never dreaming to meet with ſuch another opportunity: Dinner ended, Wine of all ſorts flowed about at a ſtrange rate, and then entred the Muſick. This, I thought with my ſelf, was brave; but, being a ſtranger, <hi>I</hi> had ſo much wit at that time to think that ſilence beſt became me, and ſo I attended the ſequel. When after many Carrouſes and paſſing of Healths, a Youth with much gravity, having a Wreath of guilded Lawrel on his Head, riſing at the upper end of the Table, ſilence was immediately commanded; when a while ſtanding in a pauſe, he thus began:
<q>
                     <l>YOU, who the Firſt of Trades with Honour claim,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe Occupation in with <hi>Adam</hi> came,</l>
                     <l>And which improv'd was by <hi>Jehovah</hi>'s hand,</l>
                     <l>And ſince adorn'd and pleaſur'd every Land:</l>
                     <l>Think on the Day that gave Firſt <hi>Edward</hi> Birth:</l>
                     <l>And tune your Voices to no common Mirth;</l>
                     <l>Since that good Monarch's Bounty was ſo great,</l>
                     <l>The Merchant-Taylors to incorporate:</l>
                     <l>And thoſe of the ſucceeding Kings, who ſtill</l>
                     <l>Have (in their bounteous Good, and Princely Will)</l>
                     <l>Confirm'd, and ſtill encreas'd the Royal Grant;</l>
                     <l>And that Encouragement we ſhould not want,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Seven</hi> of the Princely number daign'd to be,</l>
                     <l>At ſundry times, of Merchant-Taylors free.</l>
                     <l>Then let none dare to ſlight us, ſince we prove</l>
                     <l>Antiquity, and <hi>England</hi>'s Monarch's Love.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Upon the recital of theſe Lines, every one gave a great ſhout; and ſo, after the going round of many Healths upon the former occaſion, this Song enſued.</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="song">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:99890:18"/>
                     <head>The SONG on St. <hi>Guillielmus</hi> Day.</head>
                     <lg n="1">
                        <head>[1]</head>
                        <l>HAppy, happy are we all,</l>
                        <l>We they Merchant-Taylors call;</l>
                        <l>Who live ſtill free from care and ſtrife,</l>
                        <l>And ever lead a merry Life.</l>
                        <l>At our Work we ſit and ſing,</l>
                        <l>Which does Profit to us bring;</l>
                        <l>Whilſt we make the World look gay</l>
                        <l>With our rich and warm Array.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="2">
                        <head>[2]</head>
                        <l>Come drink, come drink to <hi>Edward</hi> Firſt,</l>
                        <l>And ſo in order to the reſt:</l>
                        <l>Who of our happy Company</l>
                        <l>Have condeſcended to be free.</l>
                        <l>Then round again Boys, let it go,</l>
                        <l>To our Proſperity: And ſo</l>
                        <l>Jolly, jolly let us live,</l>
                        <l>And never fear to work and thrive.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>This Song ended, after much dancing and merriment, the Company broke up, and ſo, with many thanks, I took leave of my Country-man, but withal demanded the reaſon of this Meeting; who told me, it was Annually held by the young Men of that Profeſſion, on St. <hi>Guillielmus</hi> day, in honour of him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſo we parted; and from that very time I could never reſt, till I had ſent for my Mother to Town, and prevailed with h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r, to take me from my Uncle, and put me to this Trade.</p>
               <p>Well, <hi>ſaid</hi> Hawkwood, for what you have already revealed, I muſt in gratitude return you Thanks, though, as to ſome part of what you have laſt ſaid, I would not have you to take me for a ſtranger to it, as having been a Member of this Annual Society: But waving other matters, for Brevities ſake, ſeeing (as I remember, if I miſtake not) you ſaid you have been croſſed in Love, and that That was the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of your Undertaking to travel; let me intreat you to lay your further obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions upon me, in giving me ſome account of what paſſed or happened, as to That. <hi>To this</hi> Lovewell <hi>conſented, and ſo proceeded in the Relation: As you will find it in the following Chapter.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:99890:18"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIV. </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lovewell</hi> declares how he fell in love with <hi>Lamira;</hi> deſcribes her Excellent Beauty. How he firſt diſcover'd his Affections to her; and what ſtratagem he afterward uſed to have her company, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>THe Love-Story being agreed upon, our new Adventurer, e're he could proceed, fetched a deep ſigh; when as theſe words enſued:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I obtained, <hi>ſaid he,</hi> as you have heard, the favour of the good old Woman, my Mother, to be removed from my penurious Uncle of the Gentle-Craft, to one <hi>Live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> a Profeſſor of Limb-trimming, and Brother to the Merchant-Taylors; by which removal I found my condition wonderfully altered; for now I had both Plenty and Eaſe, whereas before I had both Labour and Hunger: ſo that conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding my ſelf a fortunate fellow, I ſoon grew expert at my Trade, ſtriving by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry and behaviour to be profitable to my Maſter, and obliging to all: Nor (as I think) did my expectation fail me, eſpecially in the main; ſo that in relyance upon my fidelity, I had leave to do what I liſt, and was all in all, in taking the Meaſure of ſuch Cuſtomers as we dealt with; and indeed we had a very full Employment. Now it ſo happened, when I was juſt out of my time, amongſt other young Gentlewomen (for amongſt them lay the ſtreſs of our Trade) that came under my handling, there was one of the lovelieſt Creatures that I fancied I had ever beheld: In her Body nothing was wanting, that might render it compleat; her Complexion was fair; her skin as white and ſoft as the Down of Swans; the Round of her Face incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning near to a perfect Oval; and though her Eyes were not the greateſt, yet they poſſeſſed all that could be deſired in lovelineſs, being quick, with mildneſs, and full of Love, that with a ſingle glance they darted into my Breaſt all the Flames that ſparkled in themſelves; her Mouth in its kind was not inferiour to her Eyes, for being very little, it ſhut with Lips of unfading Vermilion, ſo that in its natural frame, it preſented an Object not to be parallel'd for Beauty; and when again it opened either to laugh or ſpeak, it alwaies afforded a Thouſand new charms; and what has been ſaid of her pretty Mouth, may likewiſe be ſaid of her fair Hands, which by their nimbleneſs and dexterity in the ſmalleſt actions, ſeemed to embeliſh themſelves; but more might be ſpoken of the ſoveraign Beauty of her Neck and Snowy Breaſts, which appeared to be the Maſter-pieces of Nature: Her ſtature was not of the talleſt, but ſuch as could not chuſe but pleaſe: And as for her Gait, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs, and Preſence, they promiſed ſo much, that nothing cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d be more. This beauteous Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, I ſay, I had the happineſs to wait on in her Chamber, being a Neighbours Daughter not far diſtant from our Houſe, there to take meaſure of her whoſe pretty Waiſt not much exceeded a ſpan; and from that hour her Eyes took meaſure on my Heart, glancing their Beams of Lightning from end to end, and kindled a Feaver in my Breaſt! <hi>And with that he fetched another ſigh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Well <hi>ſaid</hi> Hawkwood, (<hi>who at this deſcription began to look pale, fancying it could be none but his</hi> Dorinda, <hi>but for that his Maſter only furniſhed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Men with Clothes,</hi> &amp;c.) And how did you order your matter afterward? Her Clothes being made (<hi>continued</hi> Lovewell) with all the Art and Dexterity I could uſe, the better to pleaſe, I carried them home, and as I wiſhed, they were wonderfully liked; and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:99890:19"/> whilſt ſhe ſed her fancy on the neatneſs of her Apparel, I feaſted mine, even to Luxury, upon her lovely face, and ſo we both were pleaſed, but not the way at that time that I wiſhed, though ſhe told me, I had ſo well ſatisfied her, that ſhe would make further uſe of me, as occaſion required, and withal, offered me a piece of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney for my diligence; whereby ſomewhat emboldened, (there being none to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hear us) under pretence of receiving the Coyn, I took her by the delicate hand, and giving it a gentle ſqueeze, with an amorous look that (no doubt) darted flame into her tender ſoul, ſaid: Ah Madam, 'tis not this, but ſomething elſe I would have, if I durſt preſume to ask it. Why, <hi>ſaid ſhe,</hi> if it be your money you want, if you have your Bill about you, let me ſee it, and I'le fetch it you ſtraight. Ah! no, <hi>replyed I, and fetched a deep ſigh,</hi> it is not that, but that which is more valuable to me than any thing upon Earth, that I have power to name. Why, what is it? <hi>(ſaid ſhe, ſpeaking with a glance that ſparkled goodneſs)</hi> prithee tell me, that I may know as well as you; it may be I may help you to it. With that growing yet more bold, I bending one Knee to the ground, and kiſſing her fair hand, breathed out in a ſoft tone theſe words, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Dear Madam, it is your leave to love you: Upon this ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to ſmile, and look earneſtly upon me; but whilſt I was with impatience expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her anſwer, in came her Mother, and broke off my Scene of happineſs; ſo that out of hopes to ſay any more, or hear any Anſwer at that time, I departed; not without ſome glimmering of joy, to wait a more favourable opportunity: Only thus much by her Mothers coming I gained, to know her Name was <hi>Lamira,</hi> the fair <hi>Lamira,</hi> the charming ſweet <hi>Lamira.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And how (<hi>ſaid</hi> Hawkwood) did you proceed after that? or What ſucceſs had you? I was reſtleſs (<hi>replyed</hi> Lovewell) and uneaſie for many days, plotting and contriving a hundred ways to gain an opportunity, to let her know the wound her Eyes had made, and in the end was ſo favoured by my Stars, that boldly adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turing, I put my ſelf in an exceeding Rich Female-Garb, (being then young and Beardleſs) and ſo got admittance to ſpeak with her, and found (when I had to her no little wonder diſcover'd my ſelf) that ſhe was not any ways averſe; inſomuch, that under the pretence of being one of her School-fellows, <hi>I</hi> had the opportunity of waiting on her, as often as (for fear of ſuſpition) I found it convenient; and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, with the good liking of her Parents, we went abroad together, on Foot, and in a Coach, ſealing in concluſion each others Heart, in mutual vows, and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations were over-and-above caſt in, that Mankind is capable of expreſſing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:99890:19"/>
               <head>CHAP. XV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>He tells how the Love-Intreagues were diſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ver'd by old <hi>Ciſly</hi> the Servant-Wench, to the Parents of <hi>Lamira;</hi> And how ſhe being thereupon confined to her Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, he adventured down the Chimney, and found an opportunity to free her, by the means of a Bears Skin: And what comically happened on that occaſion.</p>
               </argument>
               <figure/>
               <p>ANd now I thought my ſelf as happy as man could wiſh, and ſeemed to look down upon the World with pitty, not imagining there was any felicity, but what was centered in my Heart. But when I was in the midſt of this extaſie, coming one day to viſit my Miſtris, I found her overwhelmed with ſorrow, and that by the Tears ſhe had ſhed, the Luſtre of her ſparkling Eyes were much impaired; whereupon in much ſurprize I asked the cauſe, as thinking ſhe began to repent of what ſhe had promiſed, but found the contrary, for her grief proceeded from the propoſal of a Match, which her Parents highly approved, and ſtrongly preſſed her to conſent to, in lucre of her large Eſtate, and that the Lover was no leſs enamoured than ſhe was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe. This ſtruck me with a cold damp to the heart, and deadned all my Joys; but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting her in the beſt manner, it was agreed between us, That to prevent the trouble of his nauſious viſits, and the danger that delay might breed, we ſhould the following Sunday joyn our Hands, as Love had joyned our Hearts; and ſo with a kiſs and amorous ſmile, I cheer'd up the beauteous face of fair <hi>Lamira,</hi> which before was clouded with anxiety and ſorrow: But ſo it unfortunately happened, That when we were about to take our leave, in comes the new Lover, and having firſt ſaluted my Miſtris, he fell
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:99890:20"/> to doing the like to me, and from that, to the entertaining us with much impertinent diſcourſe, eſpecially about his Love to <hi>Lamira,</hi> and what Mountains ſhe might expect, if ſhe would condeſcend to his deſire; entreating me at the ſame time, if I was mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, (as he believed by my Womanly Countenance I was) to let her know, in his abſence, the many Joys that attended a Matrimonial Eſtate; which I faithfully promiſed to perform, and indeed any thing elſe that he could requeſt, to be rid of his company, of which (as I well p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rceived) my Miſtris was but too ſick: Not that I feared ſuch a Rival, had her Conſtancy been leſs, by reaſon he was not only old, but much deformed and impaired in his natural ſhape and conditions: And indeed, as I could wiſh, there came an haſty Meſſenger to inform him, his Houſe was on fire; upon which, in much conſternation and confuſion, he abruptly took his leave; though in the end I perceived, by the Laughter of my Miſtris, that this falſe Alarum was given by her advice, that we might have the better leiſure and opportunity to proceed further in diſcourſe about our Marriage; but that proved our misfortune: for an old Wench, whom <hi>Improſpero</hi> had well bribed to ſollicite his Cauſe, having out of curioſity to hear our Diſcourſe, (contrary to our knowledge) hid her ſelf behind the Hangings, &amp; perceiving by the earneſtneſs of our Expreſſions, the repeated Vows of Conſtancy and Fidelity, together with the tender Embraces, Kiſſes, and Careſſes, that paſſed between us, that ſuch Love could not well proceed from meer Complement, or be conſiſtent in One of the Female Sex to another; ſhe, from that time began to ſuſpect, there was more in it than ſo; and thereupon more narrowly watching my Behaviour, Gait, marking my Voice, Limbs, and other matters, and being a ſeaſon'd Stick at Intreagues, ſhe no longer doubted, but that I was not what <hi>I</hi> ſeemed; nor did ſhe delay to acquaint <hi>Improſpero</hi> with her Thoughts; who finding himſelf abuſed, as to the Relation of the Fire, ſoon after my departure returned, and he imparted as much to the Mother of the fair <hi>Lamira,</hi> who ſearching her Desk, unhappily found a Copy of Verſes <hi>I</hi> had written in praiſe of her, and ſubſcribed with my Name, and ſome other Papers that had paſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us: Nor was it long e're the Father was acquainted with what they had gathered by circumſtances; ſo that the Houſe was in a ſecret conſternation; and my Miſtris had no more time, than juſt to ſend me word, our Intreague was diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, before ſhe was cloſely confined to her Chamber, under the guard and care of her that had betray'd us. This, you may well think, was killing News to me, and for a time made me almoſt beſide my ſelf; for now my diſguiſe, I found, was no more available, but might rather confirm the matter; ſometimes I thought to revenge the Treachery; at other times, how <hi>I</hi> might releaſe my Miſtris; and often burſt out into Tears, to think that for my cauſe, and that for the ſake of Love, ſo fair a Creature ſhould be ſo roughly handled, and wiſhed that any misfortune might have befallen me, ſo ſhe was no partaker of it. And now my ſtudy was to gain intelligence, in which Room ſhe was confined, reſolving at any hazard to ſpeak with, and comfort her in the beſt wiſe: Nor was it long e're I gained it from a little Youth, belonging to the Houſe, whom I had found abroad, and tempted to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery with divers trifles of no great value; but ſurveying the place at a diſtance, I found the acceſs wonderful difficult; yet, What will not Love do, where it does truly center? I getting me the Skin of a Bear, with a Head ſo artificial, that much curioſity muſt be uſed in diſtinguiſhing it from that of a live one; and ſo fit I framed this covering for my purpoſe, that when I was wrapped in it, I ſeemed no other than the very Creature I repreſented; and ſo the ſucceeding night lay in Ambuſh, in
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:99890:20"/> order to ruſh up Stairs, and force my Miſtriſſes Guards, whom I knew (through fear and diſmay) would leave their Charge, and then preſently diſcover my ſelf to her, and convey her thence: But finding no opportunity to do this, by reaſon I could perceive none of the outward Doors open, <hi>I</hi> thought upon getting in at the Window, but found many of them ſtrongly Barred with Iron; and ſo, whilſt I began to deſpair of putting my Deſign in Practice, it luckily came into my Head, that if I could get to the top of the Houſe, I might deſcend the Chimney, and by that means come into her Chamber; and upon this wild Adventure I reſolved; but miſtaking the Funnel, I happened into the next to it, where I found the old <hi>Ciſly</hi> (with whom <hi>Improſpero,</hi> it ſeems, had been carrouſing in the abſence of her Maſter and Miſtris) faſt aſleep, with a winking Candle by her, and the Key in her Lap, which I taking up, lay'd aſide my Hairy Garment, and unlocked the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, where I found her reading very penſive; at firſt ſight of me ſhe was ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed; but perceiving who I was, we embraced each other with all the endearing Careſſes that within the Bounds of Modeſty can be imagined, and then (like mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Turtles) complained to each other of our hard Misfortune; ſhe telling me how ſhe had been preſſed, and almoſt tired with <hi>Improſpero</hi>'s nauſeous Love; and how ſevere her Parents had been to her, in her ſtrict reſtraint; what Threatnings they uſed, if ſhe diſobeyed; with many other matters: And withal, demanded how I got the liberty to be admitted; the which I giving her to underſtand, we in the end fell to plotting, how at that time we might eſcape, ſeeing Fortune had ſo far favoured my Enterprize; but in that found many difficulties: For the Father, Mother, <hi>Improſpero,</hi> and the Lad, being gone to Supper at a Neighbour's Houſe, had taken all the Keys of the outward Doors with them: Through the Windows we could not get, neither was it convenient, or poſſible, for my Miſtris to clamber out at the top of the Chimney; wherefore the gagging or binding old <hi>Ciſly</hi> (for ſo was the Wench called) we imagined, might prove as diſadvantageous, as if <hi>Vliſſes</hi> had killed the <hi>Polyphem:</hi> Wherefore cudgeling my Brains for a while, I at laſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to make a Bug-bear of the Wench; and thereupon, as Fortune would have it, in the almoſt inſenſible condition ſhe was in, I clapped my Bears-Skin about her, and ſo well buckled it on, (whilſt ſhe thought probably, that ſome body was wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping her in a Rugg, for fear of catching Cold) that now ſhe appeared all over a Beaſt.</p>
               <p>Having thus done, we went down Stairs, and bolted the Door on the inſide, and ſo hid our ſelves in a Nook, or behind the Geaum of the Wall, to expect the event, and weather the utmoſt that might befall. Now ſo it fell out, that ſoon after the good People coming home, and not being able with their Keys to get Entrance, miſtruſting ſomewhat more than ordinary, fell to knocking and thundering at the Door like Wild fire, which made old <hi>Ciſly,</hi> between ſleep and wake, after a yaun or two, ſtagger down Stairs in her Fur-Mantle, the which, by the reaſon of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition ſhe was in, ſhe did not perceive; but getting to the Door as well as ſhe could, ſhe opened it, by drawing back the Bolts; but no ſooner did ſhe appear in that frightful form, but thoſe that were ſo haſty to enter, were haſtier in the Retreat: <hi>Improſpero,</hi> to ſeem valiant, ſuppoſing (at firſt) ſome Thieves were gotten into the Houſe, drew his Sword; but old <hi>Ciſly,</hi> who began to wonder at their running away, ſtaggering after them, he no ſooner beheld her, but ſeized with a panique fear, drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping his Weapon, he betook himſelf to his Heels: During which conſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nation, I and my Dear <hi>Lamira</hi> had opportunity to depart undiſcovered; to our (then) no ſmall Joy and Satisfaction.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:99890:21"/>
               <head>CHAP. XVI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How they Landed in <hi>Ireland;</hi> with ſome Remarques upon that Kingdom: How they heard the falſe Accuſation and malicious Stratagem of one <hi>Romaldus</hi> againſt <hi>Clarinda,</hi> becauſe ſhe had refuſed him, and given her Love to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: And of the policy by which he contrived to put her Life to the hazard.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>DVring the long Love-Story and Adventure, the Ship was come within ſight of Land, and the Sea running ſomewhat high, all hands were requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to bring her ſafe into the Port; which occaſion'd the remainder of this Affair to be referred to a more convenient opportunity; and indeed, what remains may prove both pleaſant and delightful in the Relation; which in due place I ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Being come nearer the Shore, they found themſelves upon the Coaſt of</hi> Ireland, <hi>where they ſoon got on ſhore;</hi> Hawkwood <hi>and</hi> Lovewell, <hi>upon their Landing, kindly embracing each other; and ſo refreſhing themſelves with what the place afforded, and paying their Paſſage, they reſolved to travel; and with them would go a pretty Youth (as they imagined him) who came over in the ſame Ship, but indeed (though contrary to the knowledge of either of them) it was the beautiful</hi> Lamira, <hi>diſguiſed in Mans Apparel; as in the ſequel will appear, to the no ſmall Ioy of her Lover.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe Valiant and Ingenuous Youths being in the famous Kingdom of</hi> Ireland, <hi>in purſuit of Fortune's Favour, and taking the third perſon into their Society, they travelled through divers places, beholding many Rarities, which that Country affords, and amongſt the reſt, admiring that ſingular Gift, ſaid (according to Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition) to be granted at the humble ſupplication of St.</hi> Patrick, <hi>their Titular Saint,</hi> viz. <hi>That no venomous Creature breeds there; and that if any happen to be carried over for curioſity's ſake, they dye. And indeed, much notice is taken in that kind of the Roof of</hi> Weſtminſter-Hall, <hi>ſaid to be built of</hi> Iriſh <hi>Oak, ſeeing (notwithſtanding the Antiquity of the Building) not ſo much as a Spider's Webb appears upon any part of the Wooden Frame; which in other Halls, built of the ſame ſort of Timber, though not of the ſame Countrys growth, unleſs ſwept down, appear very numerous. But to wave this;</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Our generous Merchant-Taylors, I ſay, being in purſuit of Fame, and truſting to the favour of Fortune, reſolving to gain Renown at what price ſoever it coſt them, deſiring nothing more, than to hear of ſome dangerous Adventure, by which Honour might be gained, and true Valour ſignalized; it ſo fell out, That being one Evening belated in their Travel, they came to a Gentleman's Houſe in the Province of</hi> Conaught, <hi>publick Inns being but few in thoſe parts, and of the Porter demanded whether they might lodge there that night; who told them they might, foraſmuch as it was an Hoſpitable place, built for the Reception and Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment of Strangers: and ſo he had them into the Hall, where they found not only good Company, but a Table ſpread with all manner of Proviſions that Reaſon could require, and Liquors anſwerable, eſpecially</hi> Uſquebah, <hi>that reviving Cordial, ſo much uſed amongſt the Natives of that Kingdom: And ſo having refreſhed
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:99890:21"/> themſelves, they began to diſcourſe about divers matters, and amongſt other things, one of them began to relate the ſad misfortune of a beautiful young Gentlewoman, not far diſtant from that place, who, by reaſon (as he ſaid) of a falſe Accuſation, was to be put to death, unleſs ſhe could meet with a Champion, that would undertake to maintain her Innocence againſt her Accuſer. This Story our valiant Youths were more than ordinary deſirous to hear; inſomuch, that ſilence being made, the Party thus proceeded:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It ſo happened, <hi>ſaid he,</hi> that an ancient Gentleman, called <hi>Ianthines,</hi> had by his Wife deceaſed, one only Daughter, named <hi>Clarinda,</hi> of Perſonage lovely and amiable, and in courteous and modeſt Behaviour excelling to a Wonder. This charming Maid no ſooner arrived to that perfection of Years, which fully diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered her excellent Features, but her Beauty captivated the hearts of many; but ſhe prizing Virtue and true Valour more than Wealth, did not return them the ſatisfaction they ſo much deſired, but (as it afterward came to light) ſettled her Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections upon one, whoſe Fortune ſeemed obſcure in the Eyes of the reſt: Yet many of them finding by ſundry Tokens, that their Loves were united to that degree, that it would be difficult (if not altogether impoſſible) for them to break the Chain, they all of them (except one, more wealthy and powerful than the reſt, who thought to overbear him either by Gifts or ſtratagem) relinquiſhed their pretenſions: But in the end, this man finding the Beautiful and Virtuous <hi>Clarinda</hi> deaf to his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities, endeavouring as much as in her lay, to ſhun and avoid him, being fraught with Malice, he turned the Love he proteſted for this beautiful Creature into Hatred and Revenge; yet fearing the Valour of his Rival, if he ſhould attempt it againſt her by force, he conſpires by Fraud, and in that he proceeded after this manner:</p>
               <p>He finds an opportunity to contract a familiar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ty with the Waiting-Woman of the beauteous <hi>Clarinda,</hi> inſomuch, that through Gifts, and a promiſe of Marriage, ſhe was wholly at his Devotion, even (as the Report goes) more than conſiſted with the Rules of Modeſty; for paſſionately doating upon him, ſhe ſuffered him, as often as opportunity did permit, to have his Freedom with her; though he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended no other, than to ſerve his Revenge, by her Credulity, on the innocent <hi>Clarinda:</hi> So that taking his opportunity to meet with <hi>Bernardo,</hi> (for ſo was <hi>Clarinda's</hi> Lover's Name) he told him, That although his Happineſs was great, in having a Virtuous Miſtris, yet he was (as many others had been) very much deceived; for that, although ſhe gave him many ſmooth Promiſes, yet in the mean while, ſhe proſtrated her Honour to another. Upon theſe words of <hi>Romaldus, Bernardo</hi> grew both angry and impatient, proteſting with his Life to vindicate his Miſtriſſes Honour, and withal, calling him Traytor to his face; but he not daring to maintain what he ſaid by force, againſt ſo Renowned a Warriour as <hi>Bernardo,</hi> pacified him with many ſmooth words; and having by that means brought him to a calmer Temper, he told him, If he would not believe it, he ſhould the next Evening be a Witneſs of it himſelf, though he deſired it might be at a diſtance, by the light of the Moon; for that, ſhe had (as he ſecretly underſtood by ſome that were about her) appointed (as ſhe uſually did) her Lover to come, at a certain hour, who, by the help of a Rope-Ladder, which ſhe promiſed to faſten to the Balcony, was to aſcend to his Joy, and revel in her Arms all night.</p>
               <p>This, though <hi>Bernardo</hi> could not well believe, yet hearing it ſpoke w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th ſuch earneſtneſs, and ſo well vouched, he conſented, even for Curioſity ſake, to attend
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:99890:22"/> at the time appointed: And ſo it happened, That <hi>Romaldus</hi> having prevailed with the waiting-Woman, called <hi>Celinda,</hi> to attire her ſelf in <hi>Clarinda's</hi> Clothes, and in the ſame Dreſs as ſhe frequently went, that (as he ſaid) he might heighten his Joys, by fancying her to be the ſame; he likewiſe ordered her to receive him in the Balcony, faſtening (as he had determined) the Ladder, and ſhe receiving him with ſuch loving Carreſſes, feigning withal the Speech of <hi>Clarinda,</hi> ſo to the Life, that <hi>Bernardo,</hi> by the imperfect Light, and by reaſon of the diſtance, was alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether deceived, and fell not only to exclaiming againſt his own Unhappy Fortune, but to blaming of her that was Innocent, in theſe expoſtulating Lines:
<q>
                     <l>I Wake, and ſee what I could wiſh t' have been</l>
                     <l>Born without Eyes, that I might not have ſeen;</l>
                     <l>Or rather not to have been born. Curs'd Fate!</l>
                     <l>Why haſt thou thus prolong'd my Life's ſad Date,</l>
                     <l>To bring me to this killing Spectacle?</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Bernardo,</hi> more tormented than in Hell.</l>
                     <l>Dye then <hi>Bernardo</hi>— How, Dye! Dye, and give</l>
                     <l>My Rival leave my Ruin to out-live?</l>
                     <l>You that enjoy my Spoils, whoe'er you are,</l>
                     <l>Since I muſt fall, ſhall my Deſtruction ſhare:</l>
                     <l>Let Death and Ruin guide me where he lyes,</l>
                     <l>To kill him in the height of all his Joys:</l>
                     <l>But is't not baſe to kill him by ſurprize?</l>
                     <l>What if her Wrongs I openly ſhould right?</l>
                     <l>That wou'd proclaim the Cauſe for which we fight:</l>
                     <l>Dye baſely then, whoe'er thou art that dare</l>
                     <l>Thus kill my Peace, and thus diſhonour her;</l>
                     <l>I, but the Blood may, if I kill him there,</l>
                     <l>The Murther ſhow, and that the Murtherer.</l>
                     <l>What need I care? Yes; but the Murther known,</l>
                     <l>Betrays the Cauſe for which the Murther's done.</l>
                     <l>But her ſtain'd blood has not ſo quench'd my Flame;</l>
                     <l>I'd kill her Guilt, but would not wound her Fame.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And thus having with ſighs and tears debated his Misfortune, he undertook to Travel into Forreign Lands, little perhaps knowing the Miſery, and much leſs the Innocence of fair <hi>Clarinda;</hi> who being ſince accuſed by <hi>Romaldus,</hi> of what ſhe is altogether innocent, in defect of a Champion that will undertake her Quarrel, is not only like to ſuffer ſhame and diſgrace, but loſe her Life: For though the Treachery has been diſcovered, it has not gained Belief; as being over-born by the Power and Aſſeveration of <hi>Romaldus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:99890:22"/>
               <head>CHAP. XVII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Hawkwood</hi> and <hi>Lovewell</hi> undertook to be the Ladies Champions, againſt <hi>Romal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> and his Gyant-like Brothers; And how <hi>Lamira,</hi> who contrary to their knowledge, had accompanyed them in Man's Apparel, was concerned; Together with the coming in of another Champion, on their part: The manner of the Fight; and their over-coming <hi>Romaldus</hi> and his Brethren; with the Confeſſion of his Treachery againſt <hi>Clarinda</hi> and <hi>Bernardo,</hi> who had likewiſe fought in her Quarrels, diſcovering himſelf: To whom ſhe was married with great Joy; and what he appeared to be.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>THE afore-mentioned Relation moving a tender compaſſion in the hearers, and <hi>Hawkwood</hi> and <hi>Lovewell</hi> being further ſatisfied, that what had been ſaid had been confeſſed by <hi>Celinda,</hi> upon her being reſcued from two Ruffians, into whoſe hands <hi>Romaldus</hi> had put her, in order to her being made away, that ſo his treachery might be ſecure from diſcovery; they both at once proteſted to venture their lives on her behalf, and a long while ſtrove and contended with each other who ſhould under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take the Challenger; but in the end <hi>Hawkwood</hi> gained the preheminency, &amp; ſo the next morning he departed, with the greateſt part of the Company, who were deſirous to ſee the end of this Affair, and came to the Houſe of <hi>Janthines,</hi> which was filled with nothing but Mourning and Lamentations, for that the day of Combat was to be the next, and none had yet (to their knowledge) declared themſelves in defence of the fair <hi>Clarinda;</hi> yet no ſooner was <hi>Hawkwood's</hi> reſolution known, but the face of things were changed, though ſome doubted the ſucceſs: But however, being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced into the preſence of the fair <hi>Clarinda,</hi> and approved by her as her Champion, ſhe truſting more to her Innocence, than what ſhe then fancyed in him of ſtrength &amp; experience, a Horſe and Armour, with Weapons, and other things, were provided
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:99890:23"/> him; nor did the Father ſpare to promiſe him large Rewards: Of which <hi>Romaldus</hi> having notice, and being conſcious of his own Guilt, made it his requeſt to thoſe that were to Marſhal the Combat, that he might not fight alone; but that his two Brothers, whoſe Names were <hi>Cormondel</hi> and <hi>Grimſallow,</hi> might be allowed to enter the Liſt againſt any Three, that ſhould dare to undertake them. This (though very unreaſonable) was (by reaſon of <hi>Romaldus</hi> great Power in thoſe parts) allowed. Nor did <hi>Lovewell</hi> a little rejoyce, that ſuch an opportunity of trying his Strength was offered: But the Youth (or rather young Lady) in Diſguiſe, who went by the Name of <hi>Lorenzo,</hi> whom I muſt for a time ſo call, ſeemed much concerned thereat, and uſed many Arguments (not without Tears) to perſwade him from it; but finding him reſolutely bent to gain Honour, or loſe his Life, ſtifling as much as in her lay, that outward grief, ſhe ſought a private place to vent it, in putting up her Prayers for him ſhe eſteemed dearer than Life. And now a Third Champion being wanting, theſe Two valiant Youths reſolved to encounter the Three Brothers; and ſo early in the morning they entred the Liſt, well mounted, and armed at all points; but then found another Knight in black Armour, and the Portraicture of a Virgin on his Shield, to Rank with them: by which means their number being equal, they ruſhed together with great fury, inſomuch, that <hi>Romaldus</hi> and <hi>Cormondel,</hi> againſt whom <hi>Hawkwood</hi> and <hi>Lovewell</hi> run, were beaten to the ground: And as for the other Two, their Launces breaking, ſhivered in the Air; but ſoon recovering, they drew their Swords, whereupon a dreadful Fight began, which filled the Spectators with Hope and Fear, according as they ſided, or took part in their affections with either ſide; and for a while the Succeſs ſtood doubtful: but <hi>Hawkwood,</hi> impatient of any long delay, laying upon the Shield of <hi>Romaldus</hi> with a forcible blow, ſmote it in ſunder, and gave him a deep wound in the Left Shoulder; whilſt <hi>Lovewell</hi> did much the like by <hi>Cormondel:</hi> Nor was the Champion in black Armour idle, but fiercely charged upon <hi>Grimſallow,</hi> verily believing him to be <hi>Romaldus,</hi> whoſe uſual Armour he indeed had on. <hi>Clarinda</hi> and <hi>Lorenzo,</hi> who all this while beheld the Fight, were in a deep heavineſs and anxiety, the one for her Honour, that were at ſtake, and the other for her Love, that was as dear as both: But <hi>Hawkwood</hi> ſoon gave them hope, by turning the Seale; for ſtill purſuing <hi>Romaldus</hi> with a forcible blow, he burſt his Helmet in ſunder, and the Sword entering deep into his Head, he fell from his Horſe, and greatly bruiſed himſelf in the Fall; ſo that whilſt the other Four were hotly engaged, he alighting, clapped his Sword to his Breaſt, bidding him either confeſs the abuſe he had done, or expect no longer Life; whereupon per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving his two Brethren diſmounted, and much wounded, after having begged Mercy, he declared the Story from end to end, as it has been related, with greater aggravations, craving a Thouſand Pardons for the wrongs he had done the fair <hi>Clarinda;</hi> and ſo the compaſſionate Lady, upon his humble ſubmiſſion, interceding for him, who had little deſerved it at her hands, he had his Life given him; as alſo had his Brothers, upon the like ſubmiſſion, and their confeſſing a true ſenſe of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for undertaking ſo unjuſt a Quarrel; and ſoon after (being recovered of their wounds) they for grief and ſhame left the Country; <hi>Celinda,</hi> the waiting-Woman being (after her delivery out of the Ruffians hands) fled, for fear of Puniſhment: And ſo the three Champions were with Triumph conducted to the Houſe of <hi>Clarin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi>'s Father, where they were highly welcomed and applauded: So that now, inſtead of Mourning, nothing but Muſick and Feaſting was to be found. And what added yet more to the fair <hi>Clarinda's</hi> happineſs, that upon the Champion in black Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour's
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:99890:23"/> diſcovering himſelf, he proved to be <hi>Bernardo,</hi> who, for the Love he bore to his Miſtris, (notwithſtanding by what he had ſeen, he conjectured her falſe) came to vindicate her, and ſtand in the defence of her Cauſe with his Life: which old <hi>Jan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines</hi> underſtanding, (at the requeſt of <hi>Hawkwood</hi> and <hi>Lovewell</hi>) reſolving no longer to croſs their Ioys, all things were prepared for the Marriage Solemnity, to that degree, that the like had not been known before in thoſe parts; ſo that the Concourſe being very great, after the Marriage-Solemnity was over, in joyning the two Lovers Hands, whoſe Hearts had been long-before united, the Feaſting con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued for the ſpace of Ten days, with Balls, Plays, Tilts, and Turnaments; in all which <hi>Hawkwood</hi> and <hi>Lovewell</hi> putting in for their parts, performed them to a wonder, and gained great Applauſe, eſpecially of the Ladies, and young Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>women, who enforced their Charms to the utmoſt, in hopes to captivate thoſe Hearts, which were not in the owners power to beſtow, as being already given away.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Hawkwood, Lovewell,</hi> and <hi>Bernardo,</hi> following the Chaſe, ſlew a cruel Wolfe, that had deſtroyed the Country: And of the ſtrange, but pleaſant Adventure, that befell <hi>Lorenzo,</hi> ſleeping in the Forreſt; with other matters.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>BY this time <hi>Hawkwood</hi> underſtood, that <hi>Bernardo</hi> was one of his own Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, raiſed by his merit to a good degree, and communicated as much to <hi>Lovewell,</hi> ſtriving all he could to cheer him, who being frequently melancholly, for the ſuppoſed a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſence of his dear <hi>Lamira;</hi> they the next day reſolved to ride abroad for their better Recreation, having now not only Horſes at command, but Arms and Armour ſuitable to their wiſh, and were not wanting to provide the like for <hi>Lorenzo,</hi> who was highly eſteemed by them both, and appeared in the Eyes (eſpecially of thoſe young Gentlewomen that were deceived in the Sex) one of the lovelieſt Youths they had ever beheld; when coming to the Border of the Forreſt, they heard a great cry, whereat they ſtood ſtill to liſten a while; but perceiving it to draw nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, or at leaſt grow louder, they reſolved to enter, eſpecially finding a beaten way that paſſed through it: When as they had not gone far, e're they perceived ſeveral of the Gentry of the Country in purſuit of a monſtrous Wolfe, which had deſtroyed many People and Cattel, and who had now not only ſcattered the Dogs, but killed and wounded many of them; which made ſome fearful Ladies, who accompanyed the men in the Chaſe, cry out, dreading upon the ſudden turns he made, he would fall upon them: But <hi>Hawkwood, Lovewell,</hi> and <hi>Bernardo</hi> coming in, by their Courage and Reſolution ſecured them from that fear, putting him to plain flight; for they having giv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n him ſome wounds, and he perceiving himſelf over-matched, haſted away as faſt as he could, without ſtanding longer to contend; ſo that they (mindful of the Game, and in hot purſuit) left <hi>Lorenzo,</hi> who was not uſed to that Recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nor indeed to be ſo mounted in the intricate Mazes of the Forreſt, who being weary, and not well knowing the way out, alighting, ſate down by a pleaſant Spring, and whilſt the Horſe grazed, or brouzed, upon the Trees, fell aſleep upon a
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:99890:24"/> Moſſy Bank, enamell'd with Flowers of fragrant ſmell; when ſo it happened, a noble young Lady, who was returned from the Chaſe, came thither, and ſeeing ſo beautiful a Creature, could not at firſt believe it was mortal, till alighting from her Palfry, ſhe with eager looks had taken a more ſerious view, and found the more ſhe looked, the more her admiration encreaſed, thinking with herſelf, that if in ſteep ſuch Charms appeared, how much more tempting muſt they be in their full Luſtre; and ſo much enamoured was ſhe, that ſhe could not refrain from ſtealing a kiſs; and upon that, fetched ſo loud a ſigh, that <hi>Lorenzo</hi> opening her Eyes, was much ſurprized, to behold a beautiful Lady hovering (as it were) over her, with looks that declared a Languiſhment; and thereupon getting up, would have mounted, as fearing ſhe was diſcovered, and that this might be ſome of her Relations, come in ſearch of her; for, it ſeems, ſhe had ſeveral Kindred in that Country, though indeed (as ſhe remembred) ſhe had never ſeen any of them: But, alas! the matter was far other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways, for the Lady being overwhelmed with a paſſion, (for a Beauty ſhe had never beheld in Man, one of which Sex ſhe ſuppoſed <hi>Lorenzo</hi> to be) ſhe began to entreat and implore her ſtay, and ſo prevailed, that they ſate down, together with the Lady whoſe Name was <hi>Lucrina,</hi> the fair and beautiful <hi>Lucrina,</hi> for which many a gallant Youth had ſighed in vain, to divert the prevalency of her paſſion, began to talk of the Chaſe, and many other things that had happened, and were further intended for Recreation, ſtill eying her with burning glances, not forbearing ſometimes to fetch a deep ſigh, which (no doubt) ſtole from her fair Breaſt before ſhe was aware; which <hi>Lorenzo</hi> often perceiving, demanded the cauſe; at which <hi>Lucrina,</hi> no longer capable of ſtifling her paſſion, catching her about the Neck, and hanging down her Head, the better to hide her bluſhes, with a ſoft, but earneſt tone, ſaid: <hi>Ah! the cauſe is here, the ſight of you, fair Youth, whoe'er you are, has made ſuch an impreſſion in my Breaſt, that forced by a prevailing paſſion, I muſt lay aſide (forgive me Modeſty) the ſilence of our Sex, and tell you I languiſh for the love of you, and could with Joy expect a ſuitable Return: Nor is ſhe meanly b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rn who woes you; but ſuch a one as brings a Dowry not to be deſpiſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lorenzo</hi> knowing ſhe was not furniſhed with Materials to anſwer the Ladies expectation, though ſhe was a little ſurprized at this diſcourſe, ſeemed to excuſe the Favours ſhe had thrown upon her, in her Praiſes and her Offers, but found her thereupon more urgent and preſſing; ſo that not knowing what to ſay or do, unleſs ſhe ſhould diſcover her ſelf, and undeceive the Lady, ſhe (after pauſing) imagined it not altogether amiſs, to give her ſome Hope, and the rather, becauſe ſhe did not know but it might be a means to deliver her up into the Arms of ſome kind Youth, who could not only anſwer her expectations, but be proud of ſuch a bleſſing; and ſo, with a promiſe to meet her the next day, &amp; in that ſhady place, to confer further of the matter leſt too long a ſtay ſo many people being abroad, might occaſion a diſcovery, &amp; that turn to a diſappointment, <hi>Lorenzo</hi> (after many endearing Carreſſes) obtained her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to depart; and ſo mounting, ſoon (by enquiry) found the way to the Houſe of <hi>Janthines;</hi> whilſt the Lady took hers, to that of her Vncle, carreſſing her ſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Hope and Fear; Hope, that the beautiful <hi>Lorenzo</hi> would keep the time ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, and Fear that it might be neglected: However, conſtruing things the moſt favourable, ſhe paſſed the night in many pleaſing thoughts, fancying, that if ever <hi>Adonis</hi> was found in the Woods, ſhe had met with him now. Where leaving her to conſider a while, I ſhall proceed to follow thoſe that purſued the Game.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:99890:24"/>
               <p>The Wolf (as I ſaid) being put to flight, and hotly purſued, at the ſight of whom notwithſtanding the Shepherds and their Flocks fled: It ſo hap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ened, that <hi>Hawkwood</hi> and <hi>Lovewell</hi> croſſing the Country a nearer way, came in with him, and after many wounds, brought him lifeleſs to the ground, before any of the reſt came up; ſo that <hi>Hawkwood</hi> faſtening the Head of that ſo much-dreaded Beaſt upon his Launce, met the Purſuers at the turn of a ſmall Wood, and by demonſtration aſſured them, the Danger and the Chace were ended; ſo that, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſome who deſired to ſeem Valiant in the Eyes of their Miſtriſſes, envyed him the Glory, yet the greater part applauded his Speed and Reſolution, giving equal Commendations to him and his Companions, eſpecially the Country people, who were glad their Deſtroyer was deſtroyed; and Night coming on, they each one returned to their Habitations; where <hi>Hawkwood</hi> and <hi>Lovewell</hi> arriving, found <hi>Lorenzo,</hi> of which they were not a little glad; and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſenting the Monſters Head to fair <hi>Clarinda,</hi> ſhe as a Trophy of their Valour, cauſed it to be fixed on the higheſt Turret of her Fathers Caſtle, which ſtood near to his Houſe, and over the Gate of the Caſtle this Inſcription in Token of her own Deliverance, and the Valour of the Engliſh Champions.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>IN Everlaſting Memory let Fame</l>
                  <l>The Worth of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Worthies here proclaim;</l>
                  <l>Who freed the Innocent from guilty Hands,</l>
                  <l>And Righted her: Nay more, a Trophy ſtands</l>
                  <l>In a Memorial; They the Country freed</l>
                  <l>From ſuch a Monſter as made many bleed.</l>
                  <l>So that from Dread and threatning Danger now,</l>
                  <l>The P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ough-men and the Shepherds ſafely go.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Vnder this Memorial was engraven their Names, and the Time of theſe At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievements; ſo that their Fame ſpread wide, and many came to congratulate their Succeſs. In which Ioy and Eſteem leaving them a while, I ſhall now ſpeak fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Adventure of <hi>Lorenzo,</hi> or the diſguiſed <hi>Lamira.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:99890:25"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIX. </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Lorenzo</hi> remembring her Promiſe, endeavoured by a Stratagem to gratifie the fair <hi>Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rina:</hi> And what thereupon ſucceeded, both Comical and Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical; With other things and matters of moment.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THe Adventure of the Lady being ſomewhat ſtrange, though Love (as I have ſaid) takes the Diadem from Queens, and where it is truly fervent, in ſpight of the nice and troubleſome Laws of Modeſty, and baſhful Nature, or Reſtraint, will blow the Paſſion into a viſible Flame; and ſo in this caſe it happened: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Lorenzo,</hi> or the diſguiſed <hi>Lamira,</hi> not being ignorant of the Promiſe that was made, after Supper was ended, began to caſt about how ſhe might ſatisfie <hi>Lucrina</hi>'s expectation, and come off with Honour; and not being willing to diſcover her ſelf as to what ſhe was, till a further opportunity required it, ſhe thought not fit to acquaint any of thoſe ſhe termed her Companions, and whoſe Hearts ſhe knew were taken up elſewhere, of the matter: But caſting her Eyes (as ſhe imagined) upon a handſome young Gentleman, newly arrived, whom ſhe conceited ſomewhat to reſemble her ſelf, ſhe reſolved to let him know the Intreague; and withal, to tell him, if ſhe had not been already engaged beyond recaſt, ſhe would not have refuſed ſo worthy an Offer, but have eſteemed it as a Favour, caſt upon her by the ſmiles of Fortune: And ſo taking her opportunity, ſhe diſcovered whatever had happened on that kind, together with the Promiſe ſhe had made: But the ſuppoſed Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man being no more capable of pleaſuring the Lady in her expectation, than her ſelf, to her no ſmall wonder, refuſed the Offer, without giving any reaſon for ſo doing; for indeed he was no other than the fair <hi>Dori da;</hi> who hearing of <hi>Hawkwood</hi>'s Renown, and by this time weaned from her covetous diſpoſition, repenting the hard uſage ſhe had given him, caſt off her ſecond Lover, and with ſuch Treaſure as ſhe could conveniently convey away, was come in ſearch of him in diſguiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lorenzo</hi> thus refuſed by the ſuppoſed Gentleman, reſolved rather to go her ſelf, than to break her word; but whilſt ſhe was conſidering on this point, withal wondering, that ſo Noble an Offer ſhould be rejected, it came into her mind, that the Party who refuſed it, muſt undoubtedly be ſome ſuch Adventurer as her ſelf, or otherways be cold to love, if no pre-engagement had ſeized that Heart, which promp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Tongue to refuſe to charming an Enterprize; and withal, ſhe began to bluſh and condemn her ſelf, for diſcovering the weakneſs, or rather the effects of <hi>Lucrina</hi>'s unfeigned love: Yet notwithſtanding, at the Time and Place appointed they met, and there renewing the former Diſcourſe, at the wondrous importunity of the amorous Lady, whoſe Diſcourſe Love ſhaping in a Thouſand extravagant Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, it was agreed, that for the better ſecreſie, the Nuptials ſhould be ſolemnized the Evening of the next day; <hi>Lorenzo</hi> knowing, that if no other way was found to colour the Deſign, it would prove but a frolick in the end; and ſo <hi>Lucrina</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing to give neceſſary Orders to a Nurſe of hers, who lived ſome diſtance from her Vncle's Houſe, and in whom (by reaſon of the many Obligations ſhe had layd upon her) ſhe doubted not, but ſhe might confide; they parted.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:99890:25"/>
               <p>The Ladies being ſeparated, it ſo fell out, that <hi>Lorenzo,</hi> in the way to <hi>Jan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thine</hi>'s Houſe, being thoughtful of the Intreague, (whilſt the fair <hi>Lucrina,</hi> no doubt, was in as large a Contemplation of her approaching bliſs) overtook a young Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man very penſive and ſad, upon whoſe Face ſorrow had made viſible impreſſions, and whoſe ſighs betrayed his inward grief; the cauſe of which (after the uſual Complement, and ſome enquiry into the Affairs of the Country) ſhe demanded; but he put it off with many excuſes, till being preſſed beyond any reaſonable cauſe of Refuſal, after a ſigh, he thus began to breathe out his ſorrow, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I being</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>born in</hi> England, <hi>at</hi> London, <hi>the Famous</hi> Metropolis <hi>of that Kingdom, and having but one only Siſter, whom indeed I ſcarcely knew, being ſeparated from her by my Parents, when ſhe was very young, and ſent abroad to travel the World; upon my return home, I found them in Tears; and thereupon enquiring the cauſe, was informed, that the loſs of that Siſter was the occaſion; who, by a ſtrange Adventure, (the particulars of which they could not tell) had made her eſcape, or was otherways conveyed away they knew not how; though they imagined it was for the ſake of one</hi> Lovewell, <hi>who (in Female Diſguiſe) had courted her, and from whoſe company ſhe was reſtrained: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, the better to comfort them, I undertook to travel in ſearch of her, but hitherto have been unſucceſsful.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Story made all the blood in <hi>Lorenzo</hi>'s Body, fluſh in her Face: Yet recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting her ſelf, and finding he knew her not, ſhe plucked up a courage, and ſaid: <hi>Well Sir, and Is this the cauſe of your grief? Perhaps that Siſter of yours may in a ſhort time return home, or you may happen to find her, nor is it impoſſible, but I may further you in this matter, at leaſt ways accompany you in the ſearch; therefore Up Sir, and be not thus diſcontented. Ah!</hi> (ſaid the diſconſolate Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman) <hi>if this was all the cauſe of theſe Clouds of Sorrow, that damp and overſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow my Joys, (though this, you'l ſay, is great enough) my Spirits could not ſink ſo low; but there is more, and more perhaps than I am willing to reveal.</hi> And here a ſigh interrupted his further utterance.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lorenzo</hi> perceiving this, began more and more to preſs him to a diſcovery: When having a long time kept ſilence, and ſtruggled with his paſſion, as loath to diſcover the mighty Secret, at laſt with a ſigh, as though his Heart would break, theſe words burſt from him: <hi>Ah!</hi> (ſays he) Lucrina, <hi>the fair and lovely</hi> Lucrina<hi>'s killing Eyes have robbed me of my Peace.</hi> And thereupon hanging down his Head, ſome Tears trickled from his Eyes; whereat <hi>Lorenzo</hi> moved to compaſſion, began in the beſt wiſe to comfort him, not a little inwardly rejoycing at what ſhe had heard; and when ſhe found him a little come to himſelf, ſhe made ſo ſtrict an enquiry into the matter, that ſhe found he had ſeen this beautiful Lady, but had never the happineſs (either through fear or opportunity) to ſpeak to her, or reveal that Paſſion, which her fair Eyes had kindled in his Breaſt, promiſing him in this caſe ſome aſſiſtance, for which he returned a thouſand Thanks, and implored Ten thouſand Bleſſings: But ſhe fearing, that by ſome words that might drop, about the Siſter he was in ſearch of which ſhe knew to be her ſelf, and whereby <hi>Lovewell</hi> might be ſtartled, ſhe carried him to another Houſe, reſolving to ſtay with him till the Intreague was accompliſhed: Nor did they delay, but went on diſcourſing about this important Affair; our young Gentleman deſiring nothing more, than to hear what <hi>Lorenzo</hi> had to propoſe, ſuſpending his thoughts between Hope and Fear; and ſo it happened in the end.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:99890:26"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Germander</hi> (for ſo he was named) being now in the Company of his beautiful Siſter, though to him unknown, they went to a Shepherd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Houſe, not far from that where <hi>Lucrina</hi> had appointed the Meeting, and contented themſelves with ſuch homely Fare as the Cottage would afford; where <hi>Lorenzo</hi> (for ſo we muſt yet call the fair <hi>Lamira</hi>) having underſtood from him the great concern her Parents were in, for her abſence, and many other things relating to his Travels, and the Affairs of divers Countries, ſhe told him the whole Story of the amorous In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treague; how the fair <hi>Lucrina</hi> found her, and what had paſſed between them, not forgetting the Promiſe ſhe had made; whereat <hi>Germander</hi> imagining himſelf loſt for ever, as to the gaining her Love, looked pale as Death, and ſcarcely with all the Courage he had left, could ſupport himſelf from falling in a ſwound: but continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her diſcourſe, as ſhe had brought him near the Grave, or Pit of Deſpair, ſo ſhe in the end exalted his Thoughts above the Clouds of common Ioy: Scarcely could he believe ſhe was in earneſt; ſcarcely could he believe that any Engagement could hinder her from embracing ſo great an Off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r; but being by her proteſtations better ſatisfied, he fell at her feet, and in token of inexpreſſible Thanks, kiſſed the Ground whereon ſhe trod; and ſo ſpending that Evening, and the next Day, in diſcourſing of the charming Theam, it was agreed; That being ſo like each other, (as indeed they were, as much as the difference of the Sexes would admit) that they ſhould change Habits, and that <hi>Germander</hi> being informed of all that was paſt, that ſo no ſcruple nor doubt might ariſe in any doubtful Anſwer, ſhould proceed to poſſeſs the fair <hi>Lucrina.</hi> At the thoughts of which, how great a Ioy he conceived, I leave to the imagination of thoſe that love ſo much as him, and would be gratified therein. And ſo leaving <hi>Lorenzo</hi> at the Shepherd's Houſe, in expectation of the News of her Brother's ſucceſs, I ſhall return to our other Adventurers.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XX. </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Lorenzo</hi> fortunately having met her Brother, and aſſigned <hi>Lucrina</hi> to him, and he having gained her love by that means, is ſet upon by Nine Men, ſent to kill him, and take away <hi>Lucrina;</hi> And how he was reſcued by <hi>Hawkwood</hi> and <hi>Lovewell:</hi> With other things that happened; As alſo, their Shipping for <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>LOrenzo</hi> being by this time much enquired for, by <hi>Hawkwood, Lovewell,</hi> and the reſt, who by reaſon of their entertaining and diſcourſing with their new-come Gueſt, the fair <hi>Dorinda</hi> (who went by the Name of <hi>Orlando,</hi> and whom for ſome time I muſt, as occaſion ſerves, ſo call) did not miſs her till the ſecond day; but then notice being given, that <hi>Lorenzo</hi> went out early the day before, and that ſhe had been ſeen entring the Forreſt, and no Tydings (though ſome had been ſent out to make enquiry) heard, they began to make many conjectures of different natures; but in the end, at the motion of <hi>Hawkwood</hi> and <hi>Lovewell,</hi> it was agreed, they ſhould ride in ſearch of that fair Companion; which they did, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of others, a long time; but finding the ways different, or paſſing too many places at once, they reſolved to divide; when far they had not gone, or ſeparated
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:99890:26"/> from each other, but <hi>Hawkwood</hi> heard at a diſtance not only the claſhing of Arms, and Armour, but the ſhriek and out-crys of a Woman, to which he directed his Courſe with ſpeed, and found on the edge of the Forreſt, juſt entering upon a great Plain near to a ſmall Cottage a Gentleman, grievouſly wounded, yet defending himſelf (though feebly) with his Sword againſt Sir Men; whilſt Three more held, and rudely handled (as appeared by her diſhevel'd Hair and torn Garments) a beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Woman, overwhelmed with ſorrow, and ſtruggling for Releaſe, which made him with the greater ſpeed make up to them, reſolving at any rate to ſuccour the Diſtreſſed; when looking earneſtly upon t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e wounded Gentleman, he verily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectured him to be no other than <hi>Lorenzo,</hi> for ſo like were the Brother and Siſter, (as I have ſaid) that on a ſudden it would be much difficult to diſtinguiſh them; and therefore being in a great fury to ſee him ſo dealt withal, he covered him with his Shield, by interpoſing between him and Death, and cryed out, <hi>Villains, What me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns this Cruelty, this Inſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>len<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e to my Friend? Slaves</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>you ſhall Repent.</hi> And thereupon, whilſt they began to ſcoff at him, and call him preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Mad-man, drawing his Sword, he with redoubled fury charged upon the foremoſt, and by a forcible blow beat him from his Horſe, and layd him on the ground for dead; which the reſt perceiving, and thinking with themſelves to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge that Injury, charged all a Front, and layd upon him many heavy ſtrokes, but the Paſſage not being verywide, he manfully defended it, &amp; ſo dealt with them, that his Fury encreaſing, he not only made them give back, but brought Three of them (through wounds and loſs of blood) into ſo feeble a condition, that they were lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle capable of defending themſelves, and leſs of endamaging him; when as thoſe who held the Lady, perceiving his more than Manly force, left their Charge, and came to the reſcue of their fellows: Now, by this time, <hi>Hawkwood</hi> (through a wound he had received in the Shoulder) by the loſs of much blood, loſing of his Strength, though not of his Courage, it ſo happened, that a croſs Lane, which <hi>Lovewell</hi> had taken, brought him directly to that place, who ſeeing one of his Friends, as he ſuppoſed him, (taking him, as <hi>Hawkwood</hi> had done, for no other than <hi>Lorenzo</hi>) diſabled, and the other engaged, without ſpeaking any word, fell in like Lightning, and ſo ſtriving to emulate or exceed each other; whilſt the Lady, freed from the Tyranny of her Guard, was binding up the Gentlemans wounds, <hi>Hawkwood</hi> and <hi>Lovewell</hi> having layed the greateſt part of them for dead, made the reſt ſubmit to their mercy, and upon their Knees beg their lives, and them at the interceſſion (which was more than they deſerved) of <hi>Lucrina.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our Champions having thus ſubdued their Oppoſers, had now time to enquire into the cauſe of this unequal Encounter, and were given to underſtand, by one of thoſe they had overcome, That <hi>Lucrina</hi> having put too much confidence in the faithfulneſs of <hi>Canida</hi> her Nurſe, in this Affair of her Love, ſhe had from time to time betrayed the Secret to one <hi>Signior Ormaſdes,</hi> and he, in revenge of being ſlighted, had cauſed this Ambuſh to be layd, to intrap the Lovers, with ſtrict Command to kill the Gentleman, and bring the Lady to his Bed by force: But the deſign (continued he) being unjuſt, our Fortune proves the worſt, though in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed no more than we deſerve; yet ſomething in the midſt of our ſorrow mitigates our woes, that is, that we have met with Honourable Conquerors, Men that knew how to ſhew pitty on thoſe they had ſubdued; and the rather (he ſaid) they hoped to find that Grace, becauſe what they had done, was at the Command of their Lord, whom they durſt not diſobey.</p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:99890:27"/>
               <p>By this time the fair <hi>Lucrina</hi> having bound up <hi>Germander</hi>'s wounds, came to return (as did her Lover) <hi>Hawkwood</hi> and <hi>Lovewell</hi> Thanks, ſtiling them their Deliverers, and would have bowed to embrace their Knees, but they would not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it, but comforted them in the beſt wiſe, excuſing (as the time would permit) the Praiſes and Thanks they heaped on them, telling them, they were ever ready to right (as far as in them lay) thoſe that were wronged, and more eſpecially, to vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate the Cauſe of Lovers, demanding withal of <hi>Lucrina</hi> who this <hi>Ormaſdes</hi> was, who told them, with a ſigh, and tears ſtanding in her fair Eyes, That indeed there was ſuch a Man living in a Caſtle not far diſtant from her Vncles, who had ſolicited her Love, but being of a bloody and cruel diſpoſition, ſhe had not only ſhun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his company, but denyed him Acceſs; for which, ſhe believed, he had practiſed with <hi>Canida</hi> (in whom ſhe confided) to compaſs her Ruin; <hi>But</hi> (ſaid ſhe, claſping <hi>Germander</hi> in her ſnowy Arms) <hi>O! my Love, I had not regarded ſo much this Treachery to me, but that for my Cauſe ſuch miſchief is befallen you: <hi>I</hi> wiſh</hi> (ſaid ſhe, in the tranſport of Paſſion) <hi>that I had dyed, e're I had put your life into this hazard.</hi> And thereupon looking pale, ſhe had fell to the ground in a ſwoun, had he not ſtayed her in his Arms, and revived her with many comfortable words, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations of the moſt entire Affection. Nor did <hi>Hawkwood</hi> and <hi>Lovewell</hi> leſs endeavour to comfort them both, with the aſſurance of their protection againſt what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever might happen, even to the loſs of their Lives; but they fearing the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, (eſpecially <hi>Germander,</hi> who imagined his Lady, upon ſeeing <hi>Lorenzo,</hi> might diſcover her miſtake) deſired them only to favour them ſo far, as to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany them to the next Port, there to take Shipping for <hi>England;</hi> which according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they did, and there ſolemnly taking leave, they ſet ſail, and with a proſperous Wind, ſoon arrived there, with much Riches, ſuch could as be carried. Where I ſhall leave them, in the poſſeſſion of thoſe Ioys that true Love affords, till the reſt of our Adventurers find them in that Tranquility.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How <hi>Ormaſdes</hi> hearing of the havock that was made of his Men, vowing Revenge, met <hi>Hawkwood</hi> and <hi>Lovewell</hi> returning from the Sea-ſhore; And how in the Fight with the former, he was beaten from his Horſe, and left for dead: And how <hi>Hawkwood</hi> and his Company left the Land; With other matters.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>HAwkwood</hi> and <hi>Lovewell</hi> having left the wounded men to ſhift for themſelves, ſome of them that yet had Life and Strength crawled away, as well as they could, to the Houſe of their Maſter, who with impatience was expecting their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, and to his no ſmall amazement, related what had befallen them, ſaying, That they had met (as they thought) with Devils in the likeneſs of Men, who came out of the Wood upon them, with ſuch fury, that they were no ways able to make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, but rather to ſhift for their lives. This did not a little diſturb <hi>Ormaſdes,</hi> who immediately fell to calling them Cowards, Villains, and a Thouſand other courſe Names, vowing himſelf to purſue them immediately, and take Revenge: And
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:99890:27"/> thereupon calling for his Horſe, and Arms, notwithſtanding the perſwaſion of many to the contrary, commanding, upon pain of death, that none ſhould follow him, for that the Glory of ſo brave an Attempt ſhould ſolely redound to himſelf: Nor long was it, e're he met our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Champions returning from the Shore, and knew them, by the deſcription he had of them; whereupon, not ſtanding to parly with many opprobrious and reproachful words, he charged upon the foremoſt (which was <hi>Hawkwood</hi>) with a huge Battel-Axe, and gave him ſuch a blow, that he had almoſt beaten him from his Horſe; whereupon <hi>Lovewell</hi> advanced to the aſſiſtance of his Friend; but <hi>Hawkwood</hi> perceiving it was but Man to Man, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated him to deſiſt, and not to eclipſe his Honour; and ſo having his Sword drawn, and not being uſed to ſuch rough Treatment, he returned that ſtroke with ſuch redoubled force on the Helmet of <hi>Ormaſdes,</hi> that he broke it in ſunder, and the Sword entering deep into his Head, he fell from his Horſe in a deadly ſwound; when taking his Battel-Axe, as a Trophy of the Conqueſt, they left him in the care of one of his Servants, who (notwithſtanding his Threats) had adventured to follow him at a diſtance: And ſo coming to the Houſe of <hi>Janthines,</hi> they found all their Company returned, and amongſt the reſt <hi>Lorenzo,</hi> which made them the more wonder, becauſe they verily believed, the Gentleman they had reſcued from Death, was the ſame; and ſo proceeded to tell all that had befell them, to the no ſmall Wonder of thoſe that heard it; and by which <hi>Lorenzo</hi> perceiving her Brother was ſafe, and had his deſire, by her contrivance, ſhe reſolved to reſerve the Secret to a further opportunity: But both ſhe and <hi>Orlando,</hi> being fearful for their Lovers, (who feared not for themſelves) leſt greater miſchief might happen, they ſuffered them not to reſt, till with pregnant Reaſons they had prevailed with them, to leave that Coaſt; and ſo taking leave, with large Rewards, and a Thouſand Thanks, they were unwillingly diſmiſſed; yet not till they were ſafely on Shipboard, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with whatever Neceſſaries were convenient, to ſerve them in their Voyage to what Land they pleaſed.</p>
               <p>Being thus on board, where little Adventure could be expected, whilſt the Sailors ſtood for the Coaſt of <hi>France, Hawkwood</hi> and <hi>Lov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>well</hi> ſuffered the Thoughts of their love not a little to diſturb them, the one complaining of Vnkindneſs, and the other of the loſs of her who loved him as her Life; regretting at nothing more, than that himſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lf had been the occaſion of her troub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e; little dreaming, either of them, that they were ſo near their Havens of Happineſs: Nor wou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d the Ladies, reſolving to try the Conſtancy of their Lovers, ſeeing ſo fair an opportunity, offer (a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> yet) to diſcover themſelves, ever conceiving to give them ſuch an unexpected Happineſs, that the Ioy might be the greater. But <hi>Hawkwood</hi> having heard how the fair <hi>Lamira</hi> was gained, became now impatient, to underſtand how ſhe came to be ſo ſoon loſt; and thereupon (whilſt the two ſuppoſed Gentlemen were retired in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in, who by this time underſtood each other ſo well, that they contracted a ſtrict Amit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>) made it his Requeſt to his Friend, that he would let him know that part of his misfortune, p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>omiſing withal his aſſiſtance, as far as it was in his power, to ſerve him with his Life and Fortune, in ſearch of her; and urged it in ſuch an obliging manner, that the other, not able to deny him, thus began:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Night</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>being exceeding dark, and Fear (that ever attends Lovers in that caſe) putting us into a confuſion, for dread that by Purſuit we might be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken, and I deprived of my only Happineſs, though the Purſuers in that caſe muſt have bought my life at no ſmall purchaſe, being Armed, and abſolutely determined
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:99890:28"/> to dye, rather than loſe a Jewel of ſo great a value as my</hi> Lamira: <hi>Whilſt, I ſay, Night wrought this Terrour, and we fled apace, reſolving with all ſpeed to leave the land, that in another Country we might enjoy the quiet Poſſeſſion of each others Hearts, by turning as many Mazes as</hi> Dedalus's <hi>Labyrinth contained, or fair</hi> Roſamond's <hi>reſplendent Bower, not Hand in Hand, but ſingle, the leſs to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived; in thoſe fatal Turnings, Oh! Heart-breaking ſound, we doubtleſs took different ways; for long it was not, e're I miſs'd my dear delight; in vain I ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſoftly cryed, Where are you, dear</hi> Lamira? <hi>ſpeak: Nor from that time has any corner of the land been left unſearched, though to no purpoſe; wherefore I reſolved to ſeek in other lands, but hitherto have been ſucceſleſs; yet my life muſt be a Pilgrimage, unleſs I find her, in hope of whom I live, and for whoſe loſs her Parents are in Tears, and made as vain a ſearch as I.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This ſorrowful Story did not a little afflict <hi>Hawkwo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d,</hi> who had not ſpared to tell <hi>Lovewell</hi> all his Adventures of the like kind. And ſo comforting each other they continued their Voyage.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How they being at Sea, a fearful Storm happened, and drove them upon an Iſland of Pirates, with whom they fought, and overcame them, delivering a number of wret hed Captives, amongſt which was <hi>Impolito,</hi> together with much Treaſure; and afterwa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d landed in <hi>France;</hi> with other matters.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>BEing now at Sea far from Land, the Wind began to riſe, and black Clouds <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lled with threatning Te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſts of T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>under, Rain, and Lightning, almoſt ſhut up the Day in Night; ſo that the Ocean growing more and more enraged, the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:99890:28"/> Ship mounted on the Waves, and often ſunk as low, ſo that ſometimes the Main-Maſt ſeemed to touch the Clouds, and at other times ſeemed hidden under Waves, ſo that the Keel was ſuppoſed to bed upon the Sands; whilſt the Crys of the Saylors made things ſeem more terrible, for nothing but Death and Ruin ſtood before their Eyes; at which indeed the Ladies trembled, and wiſhed they had not left the former Coaſt; but our two Champions ſcorning Danger, cheered the reſt, as <hi>Caeſar</hi> did the Boatſman, with his Fortune: When ſo it happened, that after twelve houres con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, the Winds were out of breath, and all the Sea grew calm; but when they perceiving Land, and thought themſelves to ſtand with the Shore of <hi>France,</hi> they found that by the force of the Tempeſt they were driven off, to a ſmall Iſland, or rather Rock, in the Sea, uninhabited, but by Pirates and Sea-Rovers, which ſo terrified the Maſter (apprehenſive of the danger they were in of being taken) that now not only he, but all the Mariners trembled, more than in the ſtorm, and were (for that the Veſſel ſeemed much diſabled) about to leave her, and make their eſcape in their long-Boat, chuſing (as he ſaid) rather to truſt to the mercy of the Waves, than thoſe mercileſs Thieves; but <hi>Hawkwood</hi> and <hi>Lovewell</hi> having comforted their Companions, forbid it, and with their Swords cut away the Boat, and let her fall off, to prevent their flight; which was no ſooner done, but the Pirate Spies having given notice from above, two Ships came out from the Harbours, between the Clifts of the Rock, and made up with full Sail, in hopes of a Prize; whilſt <hi>Hawkwood</hi> and <hi>Lovewell</hi> prepared themſelves to receive them, animating the Maſter and Sailors to do the like, who by their example took up Arms, reſolving rather to dye, than to ſubmit to the barbarous uſage they were like to find, if taken; ſo that when the Pirates (as their way is) thought to clap them on board, and over-power them with the number of their Men, they found themſelves much miſtaken; for our Champions having placed themſelves in the moſt advantageous places of the Veſſel, ſo layd about them, that lopping off Hands, Arms, and Heads, whilſt the Maſter and Sailors taking Heart by their Examples, and doing their utmoſt, the Sea was coloured with Blood; and after a dreadful Fight, the Pirates would have fled, but th ir Veſſels being faſt grapled, and finding the deſtruction encreaſe, (for now thoſe that thought to have boarded, were boarded themſelves) moſt of them leaped into the Sea, where ſome were drowned and others getting to ſhore, hid themſelves among the Rocks and craggy plates: When as <hi>Hawkwood,</hi> upon the examination of ſuch as were ſtill breathing on board, underſtood, that in the Cave of the Rock, there were a great many poor wretches in miſery, which they had taken at ſundry times, with an intent to ſell them for Slaves, as opportunity gave them leave; he reſolved to Land, and at what hazard ſoever to deliver them: When coming (toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with <hi>Lovewell</hi>) to the place, by the guidance of one of the wounded Pirates, whom he took on ſhore, he found thoſe that guarded them (upon notice of the defeat) were fled into the inacceſſible places of the Rock, by not well-known ways: Wherefore contenting themſelves to free and take aboard with them thoſe miſerable wretches, that lay in Chains, Cords, and Torture, half naked, and almoſt ſtarded, bearing the ſevere marks of their cruel uſage; together with much Treaſure and Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize, they returned; and having fired the Pirates Ships, that they might have no advantage of them, with a fair Gale they ſtood for the Coaſt of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rance,</hi> and ſoon come ſafe to Land, where they not only provided Cloaths and Proviſion for thoſe they had delivered, but upon the ſale of the Merchandizes, divided a great part amongſt them, to enable them to travel into their own Countries, being of divers Nations;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:99890:29"/> for amongſt them (to <hi>Hawkwood</hi>'s no ſmall wonder) he found <hi>Impolito,</hi> his <hi>quon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> Rival, who (in his paſſing the Seas) had been taken by theſe Pirates; him he ſupplyed out of pitty, and a relenting of the hard-dealing he had given him in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> gratified him above the reſt, and ſent him home with a Letter to his Vncle <hi>Gaſpero,</hi> with a Charge to deliver it to his own Hand, importing the Adventure of the Mad-houſe, and what had befell the Ruffians, ſubſcribing it with his Name, and inſerting many other matters he had learned from <hi>Impolito:</hi> And ſo, without making known to any other who he was, he diſmiſſed him, in a Veſſel ready to ſet ſail, who (upon his arrival) did as he was directed, to the no ſmall admiration of <hi>Gaſpero,</hi> who for ſorrow, ſhame, and vexation, ſoon after fell ſick, and dyed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How arriving in <hi>France, Hawkwood</hi> and <hi>Lovewell</hi> entred the Liſt againſt four Knights, and overcame them, and were honoured with all their Attendants; And how the diſguiſed Ladies fearing to be Rivalled, contrived to oblige them to return into <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <p>OVr Champi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns being now in <hi>France,</hi> and hearing of a great Tournament to be held, at the celebration of the Nuptials of a Noble-Man's Daughter, they (having diſmiſſed the Veſſel, and well rewarded the Maſter with the ſpoiles of the Pirates, and other things of value) addreſs'd themſelves thither, with their beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Aſſociates, whom they had all-along perceived to be ſo much concerned, as not to refrain ſhedding Tears, when their Entreaties could not reſtrain them from at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting any thing of danger, and often they fancied they had ſeen one or the other of them before, but where, they could not well imagine; they often likewiſe had dreamed (with no ſmall Ioy) that they were diſcourſing with their Miſtriſſes;
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:99890:29"/> and ſo, in theſe and other pleaſant Conceits, they at laſt came to the place where the Sports were appointed, and there they found not only a Noble and Illuſtrious Aſſembly of ſpectators, of either Sex, but the Knights (Challengers, in honour of their Miſtriſſes) daring the Combat; which made <hi>Hawkwood</hi> and <hi>Lovewell</hi> rejoyce, as not deſiring a more favourable opportunity to expreſs how much they loved; ſo that pauſing a while, and perceiving none in a readineſs to undertake them, they boldly entred, againſt whom two of the Knights prepared, and meeting in a full Career with their Launces, they ſhivered them in the Air; yet ſo forcibly <hi>Hawk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood</hi> bore on with the Truncheon of his Launce, that he tumbled him that run againſt him to the ground; but he ſoon mounting, they drew their Swords, (as did <hi>Lovewell</hi> and the other, who had paſſed in a full Career) and skirmiſhed with ſuch fury, that the two Knights Armour being broken, and themſelves having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived ſome wounds, and more bruiſes, threw down their Swords, in token of yiel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; when as two others advanced, but were no better welcomed; ſo that in the end, they kept the Liſt alone, none daring adventure againſt them, ſuppoſing them more than Men, which cauſed the Tour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ey to ceaſe: After which, they were invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Noble-Man to his Houſe, and with high Applauſe magnificently enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd; the young Ladies that were come thither to the Solemnity, and beholding their Manly Beauty, when unarmed, not refraining to expreſs an extraordinary Eſteem of their Magnanimity and true Heroickneſs, but by their Eyes and Geſture let them ſee their Paſſion went further: Which <hi>Lorenzo</hi> and <hi>Orlando</hi> well noting, and fearing that among ſo many Beauties, ſome might fire their Affections, ſeeing they (as yet) were in little hope of enjoying thoſe they deſired, they thought it high time to call them off; and therefore, having made both their Sex and the Myſtery of their Loves known to each other, they reſolved to write each of them a Letter, as from <hi>England,</hi> and to have them delivered (as ſuch) to a truſty Meſſenger, whom they would over-and-above bribe to ſilence, that ſo, by that means, they might im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately paſs thither, and by making themſelves known in their proper Habit, make their Lovers happy: <hi>Lorenzo</hi> now not fearing (at the interceſſion of her Brother) to gain her Parents conſent; and <hi>Orlando</hi> knew well, that hers would rejoyce at nothing more, than ſo happy a Conjunction. And ſo this way of diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very was reſolved upon, and indeed ſucceeded to their wiſh; as in the following Chapter will appear.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXIV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How upon their returning to <hi>England,</hi> they found <hi>Lorenzo</hi> and <hi>Orlando</hi> to be <hi>Lamira</hi> and <hi>Dorinda;</hi> and the means by which they were deceived: And how they were married by the Conſent of their Parents, lived and dyed happy; with other things; as their being Knighted; with their further Atchievements.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THe Letters being filled with ſo many known Circumſtances, and in the known Hands, upon ſight thereof our Champions were ſtruck with much amazement, and to ask further in relation to them, they knew not where, or of whom, ſeeing they were delivered by an unknown hand, and that the Meſſenger, as ſoon as he had
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:99890:30"/> delivered them, had withdrawn himſelf, they knew not whither; ſo that having conſulted each other, and finding the circumſtances on either hand wonderfully coherent, Ioy and Doubt, or Fear, ſtruggled ſo much in their Breaſts, that they ſcarce knew what to conclude; but in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e end reſolving to omit nothing that might render them ſo much felicity, as ſo fair an opportunity promiſed, they concluded to run the hazard of croſſing the Seas, having directions where to come; and ſo much they communicated to the diſguiſed Ladies, entreating them that they would bear them company, who (after ſome Excuſes in relation to the danger they had been in at Sea before, and what might further happen) conſented: And ſo taking leave of <hi>Gonzalus,</hi> the Noble-Man, and his Family, who diſmiſſed them with Rewards, and many ſignal Favours of Love and Applauſe, with a proſperous Gale, they arrived in <hi>England,</hi> not only in gallant Apparel, but ſtored with Iewels and Gold, and haſted to <hi>London,</hi> where their Miſtriſſes pretended to lye concealed, in expectation of their arrival; where the buſineſs being layd by the two diſguiſed Ladies, with the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of the Houſe, who was a Kinſwoman of <hi>Lorenzo,</hi> or <hi>Lamira,</hi> for ſo I muſt ſhortly call her, ſhe procured them coſtly Female Attire, pretending the mean while to our impatient Lovers that they were a day too ſoon, for that the Ladies had not promiſed to be there till the day enſuing: And ſo after much feaſting and rejoycing, all things being now provided, the diſguiſed Ladies the next morning aſſumed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, by putting on their proper Habits having in their other Habits pretended, that the ſame morning they would go abroad to ſee the Town.</p>
               <p>Matters being brought to this paſs, and Fate reſolving no longer to withſtand the Happineſs of our Lovers they were introduced into the Chamber where their Miſtriſſes ſate in ſumptuous Attire, at the firſt ſight of whom they were ſtruck with ſuch amazement, that they could ſca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce believe, but that it was rather a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Viſion, than true; but when they were throughly convinced of the reality, and made ſenſible of all that had happened, What Tongue can expreſs the Ioy and Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that at once ſurprized them? And now being no longer doubtful of each others Conſtancy, they embraced in fold<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ms of Love, with all the reciprocal Ioy ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable, having a Thouſand tender things to ſay at once, which forcing one upon another, even ſtopped the paſſage of their Voices, and left them to ſigh out the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part; inſomuch, that <hi>Dorinda</hi> had at that time no power to excuſe her hard-heartedneſs; nor <hi>Lami<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a</hi> to teſt how (after ſhe was ſeparated from him in the night) ſhe procured of that Couſin of hers Man's Apparel, to go in ſearch of him; nor how ſhe luckily happened to enter the Ship where he was, and finding her diſguiſed Ha it, ſhrouded her from his knowledge; nor many things more: But when this extaſie was over, fear ſo wrought, leſt they might again be croſſed, they reſolved to tye the Knot too faſt for any but Death to ſunder. But the Couſin undertaking to bring it about, with the Parents, that they ſhould give their Conſent, ſhe inſtantly ſent to invite them to her Houſe; where finding what they little expected, they with Tears of Ioy embraced their Daughter; and being made fully ſenſible of all that had hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, freely conſented, That as their Hearts was joyned; their Hands ſhould not be kept aſunder: So that the Ceremony being performed in the preſence of a great number of worthy perſons a Feaſt of ten days enſued, with ſuch Mirth and Iollity, as beſeemed the conſummation of ſo great a Happineſs. Nor were <hi>Gilbert</hi> and the fair <hi>Lucrina</hi> wanting, to expreſs the many obligations they had laid upon them; nor leſs did ſhe wonder, when ſhe knew how ſhe had been miſtaken; yet not repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of what ſhe had done. Songs and Muſick, with all manner of Varieties, ſpoke
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:99890:30"/> the welcome of the Gueſt, who reſorted from all parts, to behold theſe Miracles of Conſtant Love.</p>
               <p>The Solemnity and Feaſtival being over, whilſt the whole Kingdom rung of their Conſtancy and Fame, they provided them Houſes, and lived in great Splendor, encreaſing in Riches, and in the Love of All; ſo that coming to great Preferment, and behaving themſelves couragiouſly in the Wars abroad, for the Honour of their Country, and in their great Offices and Truſt at home, <hi>John Hawkwood</hi> and <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Lovewell,</hi> for their good Services, received the Honour of Knighthood, carrying afterward the Fame of true <hi>Engliſh</hi> Valour into many Lands; and being bleſt with a happy Off-ſpring, ended their days in Peace, and left their Memories bleſſed to Poſterity.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>So Worthies live; although They loſe their breath,</l>
                  <l>Their Fame does live, and even conquers Death.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <trailer>The End of the Hiſtory, &amp;c.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="appendix">
            <head>THE APPENDIX.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>OR, A Recital of ſeveral Worthy, Magnificent, and Charitable Acts of the <hi>Merchant-Taylors,</hi> as they are found upon Record, and viſibly extant, to the no ſmall Honour of that Worſhipful Society, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>HAving delivered a Hiſtory in it ſelf, (as I take it) not a little pleaſant; I ſhall now come to a more ſerious Relation of many things worthy of note, which I have choſen to fix as an Appendix, not think<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng it ſo convenient, to bring it into the foregoing Pages; which take as followeth:</p>
            <p>The Worſhipful Company of <hi>Merchant-Taylors</hi> have been a Guild or Fraternity time out of mind, by the Name of <hi>Taylors,</hi> and <hi>Linnen-Armourers:</hi> For I find, that <hi>Edward</hi> the Firſt, in the 28th. Year of his Raign, confirmed this Guild under the Names aforeſaid, and gave to the B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ethren thereof Leave and Licence every <hi>Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummer</hi> to hold a Feaſt, and then to chuſe them a Governour, or Maſter, with War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens. Whereupon, on the ſaid day, in the Year 1300. they choſe <hi>Henry de Rayl</hi> to be their Pilgrim, for the Maſter of this Myſtery (as one that travel'd for the whole Company) was ſo called, until the Eleventh Year of <hi>Richard</hi> the Second; and the four Wardens, then called Purve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ors of Alms, now known by the Name of Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridge, of the ſaid Fraternity.</p>
            <p>The ſtately Hall belonging to the Company of <hi>Merchant-Taylors,</hi> is ſcituate in <hi>Threadne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dle-ſtreet;</hi> ſometimes the Houſe of a Worſhipful Gentleman, named <hi>Edmond Crepin,</hi> who in the Sixth of <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, <hi>Anno</hi> 1331. for a certain Sum of Money, made his Grant thereof, by the Name of his Principal Meſſuage, to <hi>John Yakely,</hi> the King's Pavilion-maker, and was thereupon called <hi>New-Hall,</hi> or
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:99890:31"/> 
               <hi>Taylors-Inn:</hi> And in the 21. Year of <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth, Sir <hi>Thomas Holm,</hi> one of the Kings of Arms, granted by his Patent this Company for their Arms, <hi>(Viz.)</hi> In a Field of Silver, a Pavilion between two Royal Mantles, Purple gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with Gold, in a chief Azure, a Holy Lamb incircled with Rayes, the Creſt upon the Helm, a Pavilion purple, garniſhed with Gold, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As a further mark of Honour, King <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh favoured this Company, with condeſcending to be free of it; as many of his Predeceſſors the Kings of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> had been; <hi>(Viz.) Richard</hi> the Second, <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, <hi>Henry</hi> the Fifth, <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixth, <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth, <hi>Richard</hi> the Third, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And for that divers of that Fraternity trading in Merchandiſe, abroad and at home, to the great enrich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and advantage of the Kingdom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Therefore did the ſaid <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh (by his eſpecial Grant) Incorporate them, by the Names of Maſters and Wardens, <hi>Merchant-Taylors,</hi> of the Fraternity of St. <hi>John</hi> Baptiſt, in the City of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus having ſpoken briefly of the Original Riſe and Encreaſe of this worthy Company, I now proceed to tell of what more redounds to their Honour, <hi>(Viz.)</hi> They have in their Care and Protection a famous Grammar-School, known by the Name of <hi>Merchant-Taylors Free-School,</hi> founded by the Maſter and Wardens of that Company, <hi>Anno</hi> 1561. in <hi>Suffolk-lane,</hi> in the Pariſh of St. <hi>Lawrence Pount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney;</hi> and near to it, divers Alms-houſes, in which are generally placed Seven de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed Men of the Company, and their Wives, if they have any, and had at firſt the Allowance of Fourteen pence a week each, but ſince encreaſed to the Sum of Five pounds four ſhillings the Year, to each, pay'd Quarterly, beſides Firing; and yet more to each of them Twenty ſhillings yearly; being the Gift of <hi>Walter Fiſh,</hi> ſometime Maſter of the ſaid Company.</p>
            <p>At the Weſt-End of <hi>Hog-ſtreet,</hi> by <hi>Tower-Hill,</hi> they have divers fair Alms-houſes, wherein live fourteen poor ſingle Women, who receive better than Sixteen pence a week each, being pay'd weekly, beſide Eight pound Fifteen ſhillings, pay'd yearly, out of the common Treaſury, for the proviſion of Fewel. Nor has the boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Liberality of private Members of this Company, at any time been inferiour to the beſt; of which, that their Fame may live as a Pattern to others, to emulate or imitate, I ſhall particularize a few, <hi>(Viz.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Robert Thorn,</hi> Merchant-Taylor, dying <hi>Anno</hi> 1532. bequeathed by his Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to ſundry charitable uſes, in Goods and Moneys, upward of the value of Four Thouſand pounds; together with Five Thouſand One Hundred and Forty pounds to his Relations; and yet proceeding to a Charity no leſs than the former, he over-and-above forgave his Debtors all they owed him.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Thomas Whirt,</hi> who was Lord Mayor of the Honourable City of <hi>London, Anno</hi> 1534. and a Brother of this Society, founded St. <hi>John</hi> Baptiſt College in <hi>Oxford,</hi> erected Schools at <hi>Briſtol, Reading,</hi> and another College at <hi>Higham Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ies,</hi> and diſtributed ſeveral Thouſands of pounds to other Charitable Vſes.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Thomas Row,</hi> Knight, Lord Mayor of the honourable City of <hi>London, Anno</hi> 1568. a Member of this Society, erected the new Church-Yard in <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> and gave an Hundred pounds to be ſent to Eight poor men, without Vſe; and Forty pounds a Year for ever, to maintain Ten poor Men, to be choſen out of five ſeveral Companys, <hi>(Viz.)</hi> Cloth-workers, Armourers, Tylers, Carpenters, and Plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterers.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Thomas Offly,</hi> Merchant-Taylor, and Mayor of <hi>London,</hi> who dyed <hi>Anno</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>80. appoin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed by his Teſtament, the one half of his Goods, and Two hundred
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:99890:31"/> pound, to be deducted out of the other half, to be given to charitable Vſes. And thus I might name many more, who have not only been Famous for Deeds of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Conduct, in Magiſterial Affairs, and encouraging Arts and Sciences, but for Loyalty, and valiant Vndertakings, for the ſervice of their King and Country, have approved themſelves not only Men, but ſuch men, as have been an Ornament to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Whoſe Names in Fame's Record ſhall ever ſtand,</l>
               <l>Whilſt Seas begirt our happy Fruitful Land;</l>
               <l>And prove them ſuch, as durſt attempt to do</l>
               <l>Whate'er their Prince or Fortune call'd 'em to;</l>
               <l>Who both in War and Peace Applauſe have gain'd;</l>
               <l>Righting the wrong'd, and the Juſt Cauſe maintain'd.</l>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="song">
            <head>A SONG, to be ſung by the <hi>Merchant-Taylors</hi> on St. <hi>William's</hi> Day.</head>
            <opener>To the Tune of, <hi>Now, now the Fight's done.</hi>
            </opener>
            <lg n="1">
               <head>(1)</head>
               <l>THe <hi>Taylor</hi>'s a Man, come deny it who dare,</l>
               <l>He'as Wit, Wealth, and Courage enough, and to ſpare;</l>
               <l>He'l ſhew thoſe dull Noddys that ſcoff at his Trade,</l>
               <l>That to him's beholden both Fool, Spark, and Blade.</l>
               <l>Each Lady that's gallant depends on his Skill;</l>
               <l>The Peaſant and Prince do both come in his Bill:</l>
               <l>Warm he does keep one, and make t'other ſhine;</l>
               <l>Without him all Pomp and all Grandeur decline.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>(2)</head>
               <l>As his Trade was the firſt, and in <hi>Paradice</hi> found,</l>
               <l>So ſince with Eſteem e'ry Age has it crown'd;</l>
               <l>Kings and great Potentates daigning to be</l>
               <l>Members of us, as in Records we ſee.</l>
               <l>The coyeſt bright Beauties, for whom Gallants mourn,</l>
               <l>And ſigh all in vain, ſtill requited with ſcorn;</l>
               <l>Freely their Bodies commit to o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r hands,</l>
               <l>And readily yield to our modeſt Demands.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>(3)</head>
               <l>Whilſt we the ſoft Char <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>laſp in our Arms,</l>
               <l>They ſtrive not, nor bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s fearing no harms;</l>
               <l>Our Virtue they truſt, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>om others they fly,</l>
               <l>Who languiſh and ſigh ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lance of the Eye.</l>
               <l>Then a Health to our T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Boys, and let it encreaſe,</l>
               <l>Whilſt we prove good S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in War and in Peace,</l>
               <l>Live merry and jolly, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rink, love, and ſing,</l>
               <l>Cloath well our Count<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> fight for our KING.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
